<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations humbly offered for taking the oath of allegiance to King William and Queen Mary</title>
            <author>Whitby, Daniel, 1638-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30191</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11258779</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11258779</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65697)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1452:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations humbly offered for taking the oath of allegiance to King William and Queen Mary</title>
                  <author>Whitby, Daniel, 1638-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Leake for Awnsham Churchill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIX [1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Whitby by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata at foot of p. 62.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47184:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSIDERATIONS Humbly Offered for Taking the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> TO KING WILLIAM AND Queen Mary.</p>
            <q>Optima Regula, qua nullae eſt verior, aut firmior in Jure, Neminem oportet eſſe ſapientiorem legibus.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>J. Leake,</hi> for <hi>Awnſham Churchill,</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> at <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:47184:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47184:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALthough I have inſiſted chiefly on the following Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, becauſe it ſeems moſt fully to take off that ſcandal from the Genuine Members of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>which others ſeem not ſo to have regarded as the importance of the matter doth require; yet do I by no means condemn thoſe Writings which plead for taking the impoſed Oath upon ſuch Grounds as do more fully ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the Title of our preſent Governors; which as I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will diſpute, ſo I conceive my ſelf unable, by reaſon of my want of Knowledge in the Law, to paſs an exact judgment in that matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet in matters which chiefly do relate to Hiſtory, it may not be improper for one of my Profeſſion to produce what He by reading of our</hi> Hiſtorians <hi>hath obſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When by the Greateſt Councils of our Nation an</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal compact <hi>or</hi> eſtabliſhment <hi>betwixt the</hi> King <hi>and People was aſſerted, few can be ignorant with what diſdain the Notion was received, and how 'twas repreſented as an imaginary notion without foundation either in Hiſtory or Law, or with what earneſtneſs an evidence or proſpect of ſuch a contract was demanded: Now in order to the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of ſuch Enquirers, be it obſerved,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That</hi> Florence <hi>of</hi> Worceſter, Simeon <hi>of</hi> Durham, <hi>and</hi> R. Hoveden, <hi>do with one voice aſſert, That</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ubi Aldre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Archiepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopus, Walffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Wigornenſis Epiſcopus, Clito, Eadgarus, comites Eadwinus &amp; Morcarus, &amp; de Lundo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quique Nobiliores, cum multis aliis ad eum venerunt, &amp; datis obſidibus illi deditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem fecerunt, fidelitatem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> juraverunt, cum quibus &amp; ipſe ſoedus pepigit, &amp;c. <hi>Flor, Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorn. p.</hi> 635. <hi>Dunelm. p.</hi> 195. <hi>R. Hoved. Par. Pr. p.</hi> 258.</note> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam, <hi>called the Conqueror,</hi> made a League, <hi>or</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact
<pb facs="tcp:47184:3"/>
               <hi>with the</hi> Archbiſhop, Biſhops, Earls <hi>and</hi> Nobles <hi>of</hi> the Land who met him at <hi>Beorcham. To this it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed replied by Dr.</hi> Brady, <hi>That</hi> there was no Election, no Conſent of the People, no Bargain ſtrucken, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant made to obſerve and keep the Laws, which were, <hi>bonae &amp; approbatae leges Regni,</hi> the good and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Laws of the Kingdom: but, on the contrary, here is the Submiſſion of the People, the Behaviour of a Conqueror, Hoſtages taken, Towns burnt, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine committed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw. to</hi> Arg. Antinorm. p. 251.</note> and He himſelf made King by the influence of an Army. <hi>To which I Anſwer;</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That</hi> Gulielmus Gemiticenſis, <hi>and</hi> Walſingham <hi>expreſly ſay, That</hi> William the Conqueror was<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ab omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tam Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannorum quam Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum proceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Rex eſt Electus. <hi>Gul. Gemit. de ducibus Norm. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 37. <hi>Walſingh. Hypod. Neuſlriae, p.</hi> 436.</note> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected King by all the Nobles of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Florence <hi>of</hi> Worceſter, Simeon <hi>of</hi> Durham, R. Hoveden,<note place="margin">Daniel. p. 36.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> John Brompton <hi>declare, That</hi> as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Barons of the Realm ſwore Fealty to him, ſo He reciprocally<note n="(c)" place="margin">Cum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ipſe foedus pepigit, &amp; ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilominus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitui ſuo vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las cremare, &amp; rapinas agere permiſit—Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propinquante igitur Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis feſtivita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, cum omni exercitu Lundoniam, ut ibi in Regem ſublimaretur, adiit—ipſa Nativitatis die ab Aldredo Eboracenſium Archiepiſcopo in Weſtmonaſterio conſecratus eſt, honorifice prius, ut idem Archipraeſul ab eo exigebat, ante Altare Sancti Petri Apoftoli, coram cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro &amp; populo, jurejurando promittens, ſe velle Dei Sanctas Eccleſias ac Rectores illarum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendere, hec non &amp; cunctum populum ſibi ſubjectum juſte &amp; Regali providential regere, rectam legem ſtatuere &amp; tenere, rapinas, injuſta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> judicia penitus interdicere. <hi>Flor. Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorn. p.</hi> 634, 635. <hi>Dunelm. p.</hi> 195. <hi>Hov p.</hi> 258. Ipſum Regem W. ad jura Eccleſiae Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canae tuenda &amp; conſervanda, populum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuum recte regendum, &amp; leges rectas ſtatuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, facramento ſolenniter adſtrinxit. <hi>Chron. Job. Brompt. p.</hi> 962.</note> being required thereto by the Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> made his Perſonal Oath before the Altar of St. <hi>Peter</hi> to defend the Holy Church of God, and the Rectors of the ſame; to govern the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal People ſubject to him juſtly; to eſtabliſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Law, <hi>or</hi> Laws, and to ſee them duly executed. <hi>And when new Commotions were made by the Nobility and Clergy,</hi> upon their Submiſſion, and Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance
<pb facs="tcp:47184:3"/>re-taken,<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 37.</note> He himſelf takes again his Perſonal Oath<note n="(d)" place="margin">Occurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt igitur Angli memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati—ubi poſt multas dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptationes, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo Lanfranco, Rex pro bono pacis juravit, tactis Sacroſanctis Evangeliis, bonas &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatas antiquas Regni leges, quas Sancti ac pii Angliae Reges ejus Anteceſſores, &amp; maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Rex Edvardus ſtatuit, inviolabiliter obhſervare; &amp; ſic pacificati ad propria laeti receſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt. M. <hi>Paris in Vit.</hi> 23. <hi>Mon. p.</hi> 30.</note> before Archbiſhop <hi>Lanfranc</hi> and the Lords, for the Good of Peace, <hi>NB.</hi> to obſerve the Ancient Laws of the Realm eſtabliſhed by his Noble Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and eſpecially of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor.</p>
            <p n="3">3. R. Hagulſtadenſis, S. Dunelmenſis, R. Hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, M. Paris, Henry <hi>of</hi> Knyghton, <hi>and</hi> W. <hi>of</hi> Malms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury <hi>inform us, That</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Legem R. Edvardi vobis reddo cum illis emendationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quibus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meus eas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendavit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio Baronum ſuorum. <hi>R. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtald. p.</hi> 311. <hi>Dunelm. p.</hi> 225, 226. <hi>Fioveden. part</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 268. <hi>Mat. Paris, p.</hi> 38. <hi>Henr. de Knyght. p.</hi> 2374. <hi>W. Malmsbur. l.</hi> 5. <hi>p</hi> 88.</note> Henry the Firſt granted to all the People the Laws of <hi>Edward,</hi> with the Emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations which his Father had made of them, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening them with his own Oath, and the Oath of all his Nobles, that they might not be eluded: <hi>And</hi> W. Lambara, <hi>in his Book</hi> of the Ancient Laws of England, <hi>cites this as one of the Laws of</hi> William <hi>the</hi> Conqueror,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Hoc quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que praecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ut omnes habeant &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neant legem Edwardi Regis in omnibus rebus adauctis hiis quas conſtituimus ad utilitatem Anglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Apud Seld. Annot, ad Eadmer. p.</hi> 192.</note> This alſo we Command, That All men have and keep the Law of King <hi>Edward,</hi> with the Additions we have made to them for the benefit of the Engliſh-men. <hi>All which things plainly ſhew, in oppoſition to the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Dr.</hi> Brady, <hi>That there was an</hi> Election <hi>of</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam <hi>the</hi> Conqueror, <hi>a</hi> bargain ſtrucken <hi>between him and his Subjects, and that He did conſent, covenant, and ſwear to</hi> obſerve the good and approved Laws of the Realm, <hi>and in particular</hi> thoſe of King <hi>Edward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas the ſame Dr. <hi>Brady</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">P. 25.</note> Theſe Laws of King <hi>Edward were moſtly penal, or elſe of ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> our Forefathers were far from having ſuch a ſlight opinion of them: For,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:47184:4"/>1. <hi>The</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Sed poſtea ad preces com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitatis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum Rex adquievit, qui deprecati ſunt quatenus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteret ſibi leges proprias &amp; conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Antiquas habere in quibus vixerant Patres eorum, &amp; ipſi in eis nati &amp; nutriti ſunt; ſcilicet leges Sancti Edwardi. Et ex illo die magna Authoritate veneratae, &amp; per univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Regnum corroboratae &amp; conſervatae ſunt prae caeteris Regni legibus leges R. Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. <hi>Chron. Eccl. Lichſield apud Seld. ibid. p.</hi> 171.</note> Chronicle <hi>of</hi> Lichfield <hi>doth informus, That</hi> the whole Community of <hi>England</hi> ſued to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror that he would permit them to have the proper Laws and ancient Cuſtoms in which their Fathers had lived, and under which they were born and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, <hi>viz.</hi> the Laws of St. <hi>Edward,</hi> and that the King conſented to their Petition.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, <hi>When they had fought for the Empreſs</hi> Maud <hi>againſt King</hi> Stephen, <hi>and placed her upon the Throne,</hi> they<note n="(h)" place="margin">Interpella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt a civibus Londinenſibus ut liceret eis u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti legibus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti Edwardi &amp; non legibus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris ſui H. quia graves erant, ſed illa non adquievit; inde populus commotus illam capere Statuit. <hi>Chron. Job. Brompton. p.</hi> 1031. <hi>Chron. Gervaſ. p.</hi> 1355. <hi>Henr. de Knyght. p.</hi> 2387.</note> requeſted her to Grant to them the Laws of King <hi>Edward;</hi> and upon her denial of that requeſt, they again thruſt her from the Throne, and forced her out of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Cum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem haec Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta perlecta &amp; Baronibus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellecta fuiſſet, gaviſi ſunt gaudio magno valde, &amp; jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt omnes in praeſentia Archiepiſcopi ſaepe dicti quod viſo tempore congruo, pro his libertatibus, ſi neceſſe fuerit, decertarent uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad mortem. <hi>M. Paris, p.</hi> 167.</note> 
               <hi>When the</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>in the days of King</hi> John, <hi>produced</hi> the Charter of <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, by which He granted the ancient Liberties of the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> according to the Laws of King <hi>Edward,</hi> with thoſe Emendations which his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Counſel of the Barons did ratifie; this Charter being read before the Barons, they much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiced, and ſwore, in the preſence of the Archbiſhop, That for thoſe Liberties they would, if need required, ſpend their blood. <hi>And,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly, <hi>They made this one part of the</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <p>Sequitur forma jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti ſoliti &amp; conſueti praeftari per leges Angliae in eorum Coronatione, quod Archiepiſcopus Cantuari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis ab iiſdem Regibus <hi>Exigere</hi> &amp; recipere conſuevit.</p>
                  <p>Concedis juſtas leges &amp; conſuetudines eſſe tenendas, &amp; promittis per te eſſe protegendas, &amp; ad Honorem Dei corroborandas quas vulgus elegerit. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Concedo &amp; promitto. <hi>Vid. Book of Oaths.</hi> H. de Knyght. p. 2746.</p>
               </note> Coronation Oath <hi>of the</hi> Kings <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>That they ſhould</hi> conſent
<pb facs="tcp:47184:4"/>to the obſervation of the juſt Laws and Cuſtoms which the Community of the Realm had choſen, <hi>and</hi> eſpecially of the Laws of King <hi>Edward. And in the time of</hi> Richard <hi>the</hi> 2d, <hi>it is declared, That</hi> the uſual and cuſtomary Oath which the Kings of <hi>England</hi> took at their Coronation, and which the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> was wont to exact of them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from them, was, That they ſhould grant that the juſt Laws and Cuſtoms which the Community had choſen, ſhould be obſerved and confirmed by them. <hi>All which things put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſeem to conclude an</hi> Original compact <hi>or</hi> eſtabliſhment <hi>of Laws by which the</hi> Kings <hi>of</hi> England <hi>were to Govern, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be Governed, and the Continuance and the Renewal of that</hi> Original Eſtabliſhment <hi>by our ſucceeding</hi> Kings. <hi>Add to this that Rule of</hi> Grotius, <hi>That</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Succeſſio non eſt titulus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii qui impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio formam aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignet, ſed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio; jus enim ab Electione coeptum fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae ſuccedendo continuatur; quare quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum prima E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio tribuit tantum defert ſucceſſio. <hi>De jure Bell. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. §. 10.</note> Succeſſion is not a Title of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which gives the form to it, but is only a continuation of the old Title; the Right begun by the Election of the Family, being continued by Succeſſion; <hi>and thence with him we reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly may inferr, That</hi> Succeſſion only brings down to Kings what the firſt Election gave, <hi>and makes them only Kings according to the</hi> Compact, <hi>and with the Conditions agreed on at the firſt admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their</hi> Progenitors <hi>to the exerciſe of the</hi> Royal Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To this</hi> Hiſtorical <hi>Account of the preſent ſubject, I add theſe words in the</hi> preamble <hi>of the</hi> Statute <hi>made</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> H. 8. <hi>to</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Impoſitions paid to the See of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 21.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Your Grace's Realm recogniſing no Superior under God, but only your Grace hath been and is free from Subjection to any Man's Laws, but only to ſuch as have been deviſed, made, and obtain'd within the Realm for the Wealth of the ſame; or to ſuch other as by ſufferance of your Grace and your Progenitors the People of this your Realm have taken at their free liberty by their own conſent to be uſed among them, and have bound themſelves by long uſe and cuſtom to the obſervance of the ſame; not as to the Laws of any Foreign Prince, Potentate or Prelate, but as to the cuſtomed and ancient Laws of this Realm</hi> Originally Eſtabliſhed, <hi>as the Laws of the ſame by the ſaid Sufferance, Conſent and Cisſtom,</hi>
               </q> and none otherwiſe. In which words,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>There ſeems to be a plain diſtinction between</hi> ancient <hi>and</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Laws of this Realm, which the People enjoy by Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance of our Kings, <hi>or</hi> were induced into it by the ſaid Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, Conſent and Cuſtom, <hi>and Laws</hi> made, deviſed, and obtained within this Realm for the wealth of the ſame; <hi>theſe
<pb facs="tcp:47184:5"/>latter being Statute-Laws,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leges iſtae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catae ſunt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Sancti Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardi, non quia ipſas primo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerat, ſed quia quaſi ſub modio poſitae &amp; in oblivione derelictae a tempore R. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari avi ſui, qui primo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſuam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit ad ipſas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniendas &amp; ſtatuendas. <hi>Henr. de Knyght. de Event. Ang'l. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>Chron. Lichfield ubi ſupra. Sir</hi> Robert At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyns <hi>Enq. into the Diſp. Power,</hi> p. 9.</note> 
               <hi>the other being Laws</hi> Originally Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd, <hi>and</hi> Ancient Cuſtoms of the Realm, which the People of this Realm have taken at their free liberty, by their own conſent to be uſed among them; <hi>and our</hi> Kings <hi>finding thus eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, ſuffer'd them to enjoy. And theſe the</hi> Hiſtories <hi>and</hi> Records <hi>I have cited tell us were the Laws of St.</hi> Edward, <hi>or rather of King</hi> Edgar, renewed and confirmed by St. <hi>Edward, which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of</hi> England <hi>deſired of King</hi> William, <hi>and his Succeſſors, that they might enjoy by his, and their</hi> ſufferance, <hi>or</hi> permiſſion, <hi>and which accordingly He and they conſented that they ſhould enjoy as</hi> their proper Laws and ancient Cuſtoms; <hi>ſwearing alſo, at their</hi> Coronation, to maintain, protect, and to corroborate them; <hi>and which the</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>of</hi> Canter bury, <hi>at his</hi> Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>of them,</hi> always exacted to be granted to the People. <hi>To which may be added the Laws contained in</hi> Magna Charta; <hi>which</hi> though they run in the ſtile of a Grant from the King in the word <hi>Conceſſimus,</hi> for the honour of the King; yet were they, ſaith Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> the Common Laws and Rights of the People before. 3dly, <hi>It plainly is aſſerted, That the whole Realm is</hi> ſubject to theſe Laws, <hi>and to be Governed by them, and no otherwiſe. And agreeable to this Statute is that excellent Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of King</hi> James, <hi>when his Subjects deſired to know of him,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would Rule according to the Ancient form of this State, and the Laws of this Kingdom; or if he had an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to limit himſelf within theſe bounds, but to alter the ſame when He thought convenient by the abſolute Power of a King.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fourth Speech at</hi> White-hall, <hi>A.</hi> 1609. <hi>p.</hi> 530, 531.</note> 
               <hi>He Anſwers, That</hi> the King was <hi>Lex loquens</hi> after a ſort, binding himſelf by a double Oath to the obſervation of the fundamental Laws of his Kingdom, tacitly as by being a King, and ſo bound to protect as well the People, as the Laws of his Kingdom, and expreſly by his Oath at his Coronation. So as every juſt King, in a ſetled Kingdom, is <hi>bound to obſerve that paction made to his People by his Laws,</hi> in fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his Government agreeable thereunto—And therefore a King governing in a ſetled Kingdom, <hi>leaves to be a King,</hi> and degenerates into a Tyrant as ſoon as He leaves off to Rule according to his Laws—therefore all Kings that are not Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, or perjured, will be glad to bound themſelves within the limits of their Laws; and they that perſwade them to the contrary, are <hi>Vipers</hi> and <hi>Peſts</hi> both againſt them and the Common-wealth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47184:5"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS Humbly offered for Taking the <hi>Dath of Allegiance</hi> TO King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>BEFORE I produce the particular Arguments which may be urged for taking of this Oath, it may be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to lay down ſome general Conſiderations relating to this matter, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> That through the whole Series of our <hi>Kings</hi> it hath often happened, that Ground ſufficient hath been given to queſtion the Right of their Succeſſion; and in the Caſes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, and <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, the lawfulneſs of their Depoſition; and yet no ſcruple ever hath been made till now of taking an <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> who had Poſſeſſion of the Government. That ever the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſle</hi> refuſed the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> I do not remember.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> That all the Intereſts of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> plead for the taking of the Oath, if lawfully it can be done, it being reaſonable to conceive, that from the preſent <hi>King</hi> we may expect the Preſervation of that <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Defence of it to the utmoſt of his Power, not only here, but in the <hi>Neighbouring Nations,</hi> againſt the Malice of the <hi>French, King</hi> againſt it, He being choſen <hi>the Head of the Proteſtant League</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47184:6"/>for that effect; whereas we cannot reaſonably expect <hi>King James</hi> ſhould, by <hi>French</hi> Intereſts, return to ſway the Scepter, without the outmoſt hazard of the Intereſt of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in this, and all the <hi>Neighbouring Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> If we comply with thoſe who take this Oath, we ſhall prevent that Diviſion of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which may, if it be not prevented, give great Advantage to her Enemies; we ſhall ſtrengthen the Hands of <hi>King William,</hi> and of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> againſt the Adverſaries of <hi>Church</hi> and State; we ſhall contribute to the Peace of the <hi>Nation,</hi> which all good Men are bound to pray for, and ſeek by all means lawful. If we refuſe compliance, we ſhall accidentally, at leaſt, give Advantage to <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (who generally comply) againſt the <hi>Church;</hi> we, by our Example, ſhall cauſe others to refuſe compliance, and ſo ſhall ſtrengthen the Hands of the <hi>Papal</hi> Party, and Miniſter to thoſe Diviſions which may cauſe our Ruine.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> By refuſing to take this Oath we ſhall deprive our ſelves of our Subſiſtence, and of the ordinary means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for our Family, which without abſolute neceſſity we cannot do;<note place="margin">1 Tim. v. 8.</note> for, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle, If any provide not for his own, and eſpecially for thoſe of his own houſe, he hath denied the faith, and is worſe than an Infidel.</hi> We ſhall deprive our ſelves of the capacity of exerciſing our miniſterial Function, which without like neceſſity we cannot juſtifie.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly,</hi> We ſeem not well able to Anſwer the Queſtion, <hi>What it is we would have, or what we would be at?</hi> for if we be asked whether we would have <hi>King James</hi> return a <hi>Conqueror,</hi> or whether we would have him put in <hi>ſtatu quo,</hi> we muſt in Conſcience Anſwer, No, unleſs we would have <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> entailed upon us. And that he ſhould return any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as matters now ſtand, is next to impoſſible. Since then we cannot be willing that we ſhould be reduced to a capacity of yielding him ctual Allegiance upon thoſe ſad terms, we ſeem upon the matter to have renounced the Allegiance we ſwore to him; which was, <hi>1ſt,</hi> That we were then willing and inclined to yield him true Allegiance; and, <hi>2dly,</hi> That we hereafter would act ſuitably to that Inclination.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6thly,</hi> We all conceive it reaſonable that we ſhould live peaceably and quietly under the Government of King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam;</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47184:6"/>that we ſhould never be active to introduce King <hi>James,</hi> or to diſturb the Poſſeſſion of King <hi>William;</hi> and that whilſt we enjoy his Protection, we ſhould pay him the Taxes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on us. Now this is all that many of thoſe who write for taking of the Oath, and many of thoſe who take it, for taking of the oath, and many of thoſe who take it, think is meant by ſwearing <hi>Faith, and true Allegiance to King William;</hi> and therefore, according to the ordinary Sence impoſed upon the Oath by many Wiſe, Judicious Perſons, we our ſelves think it reaſonable to take it; and ſurely then, there concerns of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> at Home and Abroad; our love to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to the Peace of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to our ſelves, to thoſe Souls to whom we miniſter, muſt weigh much with us to engage us to do that, which, in the ordinary import put upon the words by many Wiſe and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Perſons, we own we cannot rationally refuſe to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>HAving premiſed theſe general Conſiderations, I now proceed to thoſe Arguments which ſeem to prove it lawful, in our Circumſtances, to take the Oath impoſed by the ſaid Act. And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> This ſeems to be ſelf-evident, That <hi>a legal Oath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>or an Oath impoſed by Law, ought to be underſtood in a ſence reconcilable to the Law, and conſequently no Man, by virtue of a legal Oath, can be obliged firſt to tranſgreſs the Laws, and then to ſuffer for ſo doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo evident from the nature of the thing,<note place="margin">Cowel verbo <hi>ligeance.</hi>
                  </note> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of our ableſt <hi>Lawyers,</hi> that <hi>Ligeance, or Allegiance is ſuch a kind of duty as no Man may owe to more than one Lord.</hi> It is that duty which no man owes, or by the Law ſhould pay, but to his <hi>Sovereign,</hi> who, in one <hi>Imperial Kingdom,</hi> can be but one; and it is agreeable unto our <hi>Saviour's Axion,</hi> That <hi>no man can ſerve,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>two</hi> Supreme <hi>Lords.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. vi. 24.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now by the Laws of this Land I owe and am bound to yield Allegiance to him who is in Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 2.</note>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:47184:7"/>whether he have rightful Poſſeſſion or not, and am excuſable and free from puniſhment by the Law, if I afford it; for ſo the Law runs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King <hi>our Sovereign Lord,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">11 H. 7. c. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>calling to his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance <hi>the Duty of Allegiance</hi> of his Subjects of this his Realm, and that they, by reaſon of the ſame, are bound to ſerve their Prince and</hi> Sovereign Lord, <hi>for the time being, in his Wars, for the defence of him and the Land, againſt</hi> Every <hi>Rebellion,</hi> Power and Might reared againſt HIm, <hi>and with Him to enter and abide in ſervice in Battle, if caſe ſo require; and that for the ſame Service, what Fortune ever fall by chance in the ſame Battle againſt the Mind and Will of the Prince (as in this Land ſometime paſt hath been ſeen) it is not reaſonable, but againſt all Laws, Reaſon and good Conſcience, that the ſaid Subjects, going with their</hi> Sovereign Lord <hi>in Wars, attending upon Him in Perſon, or being in other places within this Land or without by His Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, any thing ſhould loſe or forfeit for doing their</hi> true <hi>Duty, and Service of</hi> Allegiance. <hi>It be therefore ordained, enacted, and eſtabliſhed by the King our Sovereign Lord, by the advice and aſſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament Aſſembled, and by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the ſame, that from henceforth no manner of perſon or perſons, whatſoever he or they be, that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon the King and</hi> Sovereign Lord <hi>of this Land, for the time being, in his Perſon, and do Him true and faithful Service of Allegiance, he or they be in no wiſe convice or attaint of High Treaſon, ne of other Offences for that cauſe by Act of Parliament, or otherwiſe by any Proceſs of Law, whereby he or any of them ſhall loſe, or forfeit Life, Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, Rents, Poſſeſſions, Hereditaments, Goods, Chattels, or any other things, but to be for that Deed and Service utterly diſcharged of any Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Trouble or Loſs.</hi> Where Note,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> That this Service and Allegiance mentioned in this Statute, is <hi>faithful Service,</hi> and <hi>true Allegiance</hi> once and again, and it is declared to be <hi>the duty of all Subjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:47184:7"/>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> That it is to be yielded to <hi>the King for the time being,</hi> without enquiry whether he be the <hi>rightful King</hi> or no; for <hi>it was agreeable to reaſon fo Eſtate,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Lord Bacon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſtory of the Reign of <hi>H. 7. p. 144.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That the Subject ſhould not enquire of the juſtneſs of the King's Title, or Quarrel; and it was agreeable to good Conſcience, That whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the fortune of the War were, the Subject ſhould not ſuffer for his Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> That this Service and Allegiance is to be yielded to <hi>the King for the time being againſt <hi>every Power and Might reared againſt Him.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> That through the whole Body of the Act he is called <hi>the Sovereign Lord of the Land, their Sovereign Lord;</hi> and ſo it ſeems we need not ſcruple the uſe of the ſaid Title in our Prayers, it being only that which the Law of the Land gives to every one that is <hi>King for the time being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly,</hi> That this Statute hath continued unrepealed about Two hundred years, and therefore hath been ſo long ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the whole Nation, and judged well conſiſtent with the duty of Allegiance owing to their lawful Sovereign; they therefore judged it not repugnant to their Oaths of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to their rightful Sovereign to bear <hi>true Allegiance,</hi> and to do <hi>true</hi> and <hi>faithful Service of Allegiance</hi> to any other <hi>King</hi> for the time being, who had got quiet poſſeſſion of the Throne, which is all that this Oath requireth of us.</p>
               <p>Moreover, all <hi>High Treaſon</hi> committed by a Native of the Land, is an offence againſt his natural Allegiance,<note place="margin">n. 3. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Reports, Par. 7. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi>'s Caſe, p. 435.</note> which appears from the Indictments of Treaſon, (<hi>which,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Lord Cook, are of all other things moſt curiouſly and certainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited and penned</hi>) for they run for committing this Crime <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra debitum fidei &amp; ligeantiae ſuae, quod praefato Domino Regi na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliter, &amp; de jure impendere debuit, Againſt the duty of Faith and Allegiance which he naturally and of right ought to yield to his Lord the King;</hi> or for committing this fact, <hi>contra Dominum Regem ſupremum, &amp; naturalem Dominum ſuum, Againſt our Lord the King, his ſupreme and natural Lord;</hi> or, <hi>contra naturalem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantiam Domino Regi debitam, Againſt the natural Allegiance due to our Lord the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the ſame <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice Cook</hi> in his deſcant on theſe words of the <hi>25th.</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third,<note place="margin">Inſtit. Par. 3. ch. 1. p. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Seignior le Roy,</hi> uſed in that Statute concerning <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47184:8"/>
                  <q>That this Act is to be underſtood of a <hi>King in poſſeſſion of the Crown and Kingdom;</hi>
                  </q> for if there be a <hi>King Regnant in poſſeſſion,</hi> althopugh he be <hi>Rex de facto, &amp; non de jure,</hi> yet he is <hi>Seignior le Roy, within the purvien of this Statute;</hi> and the other that hath right, and is out of poſſeſſion, is not within this Act. Nay, if Treaſon be committed againſt a <hi>King, de facto, &amp; non de jure,</hi> and afterwards the <hi>King, de jure,</hi> cometh to the Crown, he ſhall puniſh the Treaſon done to the <hi>King, de facto;</hi> and a Pardon by a <hi>King, de jure,</hi> that is not alſo <hi>King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pleas of the Crown, <hi>p. 11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>de facto,</hi> is void. The <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice Hales</hi> doth alſo ſay, That <hi>a King</hi> de facto, <hi>and not</hi> de jure, <hi>is a King within this Act, and a Treaſon againſt Him is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, though the right Heir get the Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſitably to theſe declarations of theſe great Men, I find in <hi>Bagot</hi>'s <hi>Caſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Paſc. 9. Ed. 4.</note> argued in the Ninth year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, that it is ſaid, That <hi>the King ſhall have the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of any Forfeiture made to</hi> Henry <hi>the Sixth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes made in his time, the Brief ſhall be,</hi> contra pacem H. 6. nuper de facto, &amp; non de jure, <hi>againſt the peace of</hi> Henry <hi>the Sixth, late King in Poſſeſſion, though not of Right,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and a Man ſhall be arraigned of Treaſon done to the ſaid King</hi> Henry <hi>in compaſſing his Death;</hi> and it is there added, <hi>Qu' ſi ceſty qu' eſt ore Roy in temps le Roy</hi> Henry <hi>uſt fait Charter de Pardon c' ſera void a ore car cheſcun qu' ferra Charter de Pardon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient eſtre Roy en fait,</hi> That <hi>if he who is now King had given a Charter of Pardon in the time of King</hi> Henry, <hi>that Charter ſhall be void at preſent, becauſe it is neceſſary that every one who makes a Charter of Pardon ſhould be actually King.</hi> Now hence,</p>
               <p n="1">1. I inferr, that we cannot reaſonably except againſt the uſing of thoſe terms, <hi>Our moſt Gracious Sovereign, our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord and Lady King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only the terms which our Law gives to every one that is in Poſſeſſion of the Government; yea, ſay our great <hi>Lawyers,</hi> terms which belong to the <hi>King</hi> in Poſſeſſion alone, though he be <hi>King de facto,</hi> and not <hi>de jure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly,</hi> If Treaſon committed againſt a <hi>King in Poſſeſſion,</hi> though <hi>de facto</hi> only, by any of his <hi>native Subjects,</hi> be an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt his <hi>natural Allegiance</hi> due to him, and againſt that duty of Faith and Allegiance which he naturally, and of right ought to yield to him, then is Faith and Allegiance both his Right to challenge, and our Duty to yield to him;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47184:8"/>and then he, by requiring us to ſwear it, requires us only to give him his Right, and we by ſo doing ſhall only engage our ſelves to the performance of our Duty. If it be his Right, becauſe he is a <hi>King Regnant in Poſſeſſion,</hi> then it is his Right no longer than he is in Poſſeſſion, and then the Oath can require it no longer then he is in Poſſeſſion; and then we have no juſt Ground to fear that the Oath of Allegiance to King <hi>James</hi> doth bind us now he is not in Poſſeſſion; or that the Oaths we take unto King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> can bind us any longer than they are in Poſſeſſion; this Oath can therefore do no real Injury to King <hi>James;</hi> for if he be not in Poſſeſſion, he hath not, by theſe Expoſitions of <hi>Seignior le Roy,</hi> a Right to actual Allegiance. If he become again the <hi>King Regnant in Poſſeſſion,</hi> the duty of bearing Faith and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to him immediately returns without taking any new Oath.</p>
               <p>Again, if the <hi>King</hi> that hath Right, and is out of Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is not within this Act, and therefore cannot be the <hi>Seignior le Roy</hi> within <hi>the purvieu of this Statute,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the <hi>King</hi> againſt whom Treaſon may be committed, againſt this Act, then can I not offend againſt my natural Allegiance, or againſt any Duty of Faith and Allegiance, which of right I ought to yield to him, and then I do not ſo offend by taking of the Oath of Faith and true Allegiance to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and therefore I may take that Oath notwithſtanding my former Promiſe upon Oath to bear Faith and true Allegiance to King <hi>James,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by doing ſo I offend not againſt any Faith and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance due to him.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if the <hi>King in Poſſeſſion</hi> be the <hi>Seignior le Roy within the purvieu of this Act,</hi> it muſt be Treaſon againſt him to compaſs or imagine his Death, or to prepare by any Over-Act to depoſe him; <hi>This being,</hi> ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>a ſufficient Over-Act to prove the compaſſing and imagination of the Death of the King; for this, upon the matter, is to make the King a Subject, and to diſpoſe of his Kingly Office of Royal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Then muſt it be High Treaſon againſt Him to <hi>Levy War againſt him in this Realm, to be adherent to his Enemies within this Realm, giving to them aid and comfort in this Realm, or elſewhere;</hi> for all theſe things are by that Act made Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47184:9"/>againſt the <hi>Seignior le Roy within the purvieu of this Statute.</hi> This Statute therefore as it is expounded by the Lord Chief Juſtices, <hi>Coke</hi> and <hi>Hales,</hi> muſt oblige the Subjects of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> not to aſſiſt King <hi>James</hi> againſt them, that being <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt the <hi>25th.</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, which they cannot be obliged to commit. If King <hi>James,</hi> ſhould he come again to the Poſſeſſion of the Crown, might puniſh me for any of theſe treaſonable Acts committed againſt King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> but could not puniſh me by the Eleventh of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh for any Duty of Allegiance, or faithful Service paid to them as my <hi>Sovereign Lord and Lady,</hi> then ſure Allegiance and Faith will be due to them whilſt in Poſſeſſion, and to them only; for were it due to King <hi>James,</hi> I might be puniſhed for not performing it to him. If, laſtly, no Pardon now given by King <hi>James</hi> can ſave me from the guilt of Treaſon againſt King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and that guilt only be contracted by offending againſt that Duty of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which of right I owe to them; ſure I cannot offend by want of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance</hi> againſt him who cannot pardon me, but againſt them only againſt whom I commit that Treaſon; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto them alone Faith and Allegiance muſt of Right be due, and ſo to them by Oath and Promiſe may be given.</p>
               <p>As an Addition to,<note place="margin">n. 4.</note> or a Conſideration ſtrengthening the former Argument, let it be obſerved,</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Sand. de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram. prael. 7. §. 7.</note> That it is agreed on all hands, that a <hi>promiſory Oath ceaſeth to bind, when the matter of the Oath ceaſeth.</hi> Thus, if a Man ſwears to appear at ſuch an Aſſizes, if there be no Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes kept there, he cannot be bound to appear, becauſe <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilium nulla eſt obligatio,</hi> there is no obligation to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities; and of the matrimonal Vow, St. <hi>Paul</hi> declareth, That <hi>the Woman is bound by the Law whilſt her Husband lives;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. vii. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>but if her Husband die, ſhe is at liberty to be married to whom ſhe will;</hi> becauſe then the matter or objectof her Vow is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
               <p>Others deliver the Rule thus,<note place="margin">Ameſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Quum aufertur Ratio forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis juramenti juramentum coſſat; When the formal Reaſon of an Oath ceaſeth, the Obligation of the Oath muſt ceaſe.</hi> Thus, if a Man ſwears Reſidence on a Living, his Oath only binds him
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47184:9"/>whilſt he is <hi>Incumbent,</hi> becauſe he only took, and only was obliged to take it for that very reaſon, becauſe he was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent. Now the formal Reaſon of the <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> promiſed to King <hi>James,</hi> was this, That he was <hi>our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord King</hi> James, ſaith the <hi>Oath of Allegiance;</hi> the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour of this Realm,</hi> ſaith that of <hi>Supremacy;</hi> and therefore when he ceaſeth, in the ſence and meaning of the Law, to be <hi>our Sovereign Lord,</hi> and <hi>the Supreme Governour of this Realm,</hi> my Oath to yield Faith and Allegiance to him muſt ceaſe to be obliging to me. If when another is <hi>King Regnant in poſſeſſion,</hi> he is legally dead for that time, his politick ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity being then ſeparated from the natural Perſon of the <hi>King,</hi> then muſt the <hi>Subjects</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be free from their Allegiance to him for that time; for though <hi>Ligeance is due,</hi> as was reſolved in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cook</hi>'s Reports, p. 438.</note> 
                  <hi>to the natural Perſon of the King, and not to the politick Capacity only;</hi> yet is it only due to the <hi>natural Perſon</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> when it is accompanied with his <hi>politick Capacity;</hi> for otherwiſe he could not poſſibly diveſt himſelf of it by any the moſt formal or voluntary reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government whatſoever, nor by any other Act whatſoever, <hi>viz.</hi> the entrance into a <hi>Monaſtery</hi> out of his Dominions, and the continuance there during life; for he cannot ceaſe, while he lives, to be deſcended <hi>of the Blood-Royal of the Realm,</hi> which immediately conſtitutes him in his <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Capacity,</hi> nor to be <hi>King by Birth-right inherent;</hi> he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only in ſuch caſes ceaſeth to be <hi>King,</hi> and our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him only ceaſeth to be due, becauſe he hath ſeparated from himſelf that <hi>politick Capacity</hi> which was before apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to his <hi>natural Perſon</hi> by the Law,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> by virtue of the Lineal deſcent of that Perſon from the Blood-Royal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Succeſſion doth attend.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> It is agreed on all hands that we cannot have <hi>two Kings</hi> at once, and therefore either the <hi>King Regnant in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion only,</hi> or the <hi>King,</hi> de jure, <hi>out of poſſeſſion only,</hi> can be our <hi>legal King;</hi> or he who is in the eye of our Law, <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King, and the only Supreme Governour of this Realm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> It appeareth by what hath been already ſaid, and by the determination of the Judges in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe,<note place="margin">P. 438. P. 439.</note> That <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is due only to the King;</hi> that <hi>the Ligeance or Faith of the Subject is</hi> proprium quarto modo <hi>tot the King;</hi> omni, ſoli &amp; ſemper; it is due therefore to every one who is <hi>Seignior le
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47184:10"/>Roy;</hi> and ſo to a <hi>King Regnant in poſſeſſion,</hi> though he be only <hi>King, de facto,</hi> if the Law make him <hi>Seignior le Roy.</hi> It is due <hi>ſoli</hi> to him alone, if he alone for the time being be <hi>our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord the King.</hi> It is due unto him <hi>ſemper,</hi> as long as he continues the <hi>King Regnant in poſſeſſion,</hi> upon the ſame account.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A. 9. Edw. 4. Term. Paſch.</note> Obſerve that in <hi>Bagot</hi>'s Caſe it is determined that <hi>le Roy Hen. fuiſt Roy en poſſeſſion, &amp; il covient qu' le Royalme eit un Roy South qu' les leges ſeront tenus &amp; maintein do<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> per c' qu' il ne fuiſt eins forſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> per uſurpation, unc' cheſcun act judicial fait per luy qu' touche juriſdiction Royal ſera bon, &amp; licra le Roy de droit quand il fait regreſs; King</hi> Henry <hi>the Sixth was King in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and it is neceſſary that the Kingdom ſhould have a King, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom the Laws ſhould be held and maintained; therefore be it that he was only in by uſurpation, yet every judicial Act done by him which toucheth the Royal juriſdiction ſhall be good, and ſhall bind the rightful King when he returns.</hi> And it is there added, that <hi>le dit Roy H. ne fuit merement comme uſurper, car le corone fuiſt taile a luy per. Parliament; The ſaid King</hi> Henry <hi>was not meerly as an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper, becauſe the Crown was entailed upon him by Act of Parliament,</hi> as now it is upon King <hi>William.</hi> If then <hi>il covient qu' le Royalme eit un Roy, The Realm muſt always have a King, under whom the Laws ſhall be held and maintained,</hi> the <hi>King Regnant in poſſeſſion</hi> being he alone under whom, for the time being, they can be held and maintained, he only can be <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King for the time being.</hi> If every Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial act done by him which concerns the Royal Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be good, though it be always done under the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and Authority of <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> then muſt he be <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> to all intents and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Law, for the time being; then muſt the Laws made by him be good alſo, though they run in the ſtile of <hi>our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord the King,</hi> or <hi>our Lord the King.</hi> And if all this be true of a <hi>King Regnant,</hi> or <hi>in poſſeſſion</hi> though it ſhould be granted that he held the Kingdom meerly by uſurpation, it muſt more certainly be true of one on whom <hi>the Kingdom is entailed by Act of Parliament,</hi> as in our caſe it is, and who is therefore not to be looked on as <hi>a meer <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 434.</note> Obſerve that in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe it is determined, that, <hi>Protectio trahit ſubjectionem &amp; ſubjectio protectionem,</hi> Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requires Subjection, and Subjection Protection. <hi>Quia ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47184:10"/>ſubditus Regi tenetur ad Obedientiam, ita Rex ſubdiot tenetur ad Protectionem;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 436, 437.</note> 
                  <hi>For as the Subject oweth to the King his true and faithful Ligeance and Obedience; ſo the Sovereign is to govern and protect his Subjects;</hi> that <hi>Power and Protection draweth Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> and that <hi>the Ligeance of the Subject is of as great extent and latitude as the Royal Power and Protection of the King;</hi> that <hi>though the King in his natural Perſon is ſubject to Death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 438.</note> 
                  <hi>Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet in his politick Capacity he is eſteem'd to be Immortal, not ſubject to Death, Infirmity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now I would not hence inferr with others, that I owe a King no Subjection or Allegiance any longer than he doth actually protect me; or that, if he neglect his duty in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting me in my Goods or Body, or of protecting the Laws, (according to theſe wordds of <hi>Foreteſcue, Rex ad tutelam legis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>corporum &amp; bonorum erectus eſt,</hi>) I may neglect my duty of Allegiance to him.</p>
               <p>But yet I think it reaſonable hence to inferr affirmatively, <q>From the King Regnant in poſſeſſion, I, for the time being, do receive Protection; therefore to him for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I do not owe Subjection. Protection draws Allegiance, therefore Protection from him draws Allegiance to him. The Ligeanceof the Subject is of as great extent and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude as is the Royal Power and Protection of the King; therefore it muſt extend it ſelf unto all times and places in which, and where this Royal Power is exerted, and this Protection is afforded to me.<note place="margin">Rom. xiij. 1, 4.</note>
                  </q> St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth found the reaſon of our Subjection, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to the preſent Powers,</hi> on this ground, That they are unto us <hi>the Miniſters of God for good;</hi> or in the words of Chriſt, that they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Benefactors;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. xxij 25.</note> to whom we therefore own Subjection on the ſcore of gratitude, as far as we with juſtice can afford it. <q>Since therefore, ſaith the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De legum Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. lec. 5. §. 18.</note> we owe it to the Supreme Powers, even when they are uſurped, that we enjoy what is our own, that we live ſafe from ſlaughter, and from rapine; yea that we live at all ſince without them we neither could have remedy or ſafe-guard againſt the Luſts, the Furies, or the Injuries of wicked Men; 'tis the moſt equitable thing, and that which the Old Law of giving and receiving mutually doth require, that for ſo many and great benefits we ſhould make ſome return unto that Power which affords them:</q>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:47184:11"/>And what is that Return, he doth ſufficiently explain in the enſuing words, <hi>Profecto perfecto perverſiſſimae mentis eſt, 'Tis certainly an indication of a moſt perverſe mind to deſire to live under the Patronage of his Government whom you will not obey, and to refuſe to be governed by him whoſe Protection you enjoy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, if the <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>politick Capacity</hi> doth never die, and yet the <hi>King</hi> out of poſſeſſion is no <hi>King,</hi> as to that <hi>politick Capacity,</hi> or as to all intents and purpoſes of Law; then the <hi>King Regnant</hi> in poſſeſſion muſt be <hi>King</hi> for all the ſame intents and purpoſes, or there muſt be an <hi>Interregnum,</hi> which yet our Law will not admit of.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lord Bacon</hi> Tells us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>n. 5.</hi> Hiſtory of the Reign of <hi>H. 7. p. 144. 1 Chr. xxj. 17.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>the Spirit of this Law was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully pious and noble, being like in matter of War to the Spirit of</hi> David <hi>in matter of Plague, who ſaith, Is it not I that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the people to be numbred? even I it is that have ſinned, and done evil indeed; but theſe ſheep, what have they done? Let thy hand, I pray thee, O Lord my God, be upon me, and on my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, but not on thy people that they ſhould be plagued.</hi> The equity of which Prayer is built on this foundation, That <hi>they who had no hand in the ſin, ſhould bear no ſhare in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ſhould not be dealt with, <hi>ut oves quae ducuntur ad mortem, neque evadere poſſunt, As ſheep led to the ſlaughter, which they cannot avoid.</hi> This, applied unto the preſent Law, runs thus: They who have had no ſhare in he Sin, if any he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in that Revolution which hath diſpoſſeſſed the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Right,</hi> and given poſſeſſion to the King <hi>de facto,</hi> ſhould have no ſhare in the Puniſhment, and ſhould not be brought into an unavoidable neceſſity of being ruined, and undone by it. But now, without the benefit of this Law of <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, and on the ſuppoſition of a neceſſity ſtill laid upon them to retain Faith and Allegiance to the rightful <hi>King,</hi> though out of poſſeſſion, and to deny it, whatever they may ſuffer by ſo doing, to the <hi>King Regnant,</hi> or in poſſeſſion as aforeſaid, they muſt be under an unavoidable neceſſity of being ruined, and undone; for they cannot reaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Protection from the <hi>King Regnant,</hi> if they deny him their <hi>Allegiance;</hi> and not only ſo, but declare they hold themſelves in Conſcience bound to give it to his Enemies; nor can they hope to eſcape thoſe Penalties which are at preſent, or may hereafter be impoſed on all who ſhall refuſe to promiſe <hi>they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47184:11"/>will bear. Faith and true Allegiance</hi> to him; and ſo the more honeſt, and the better Subject any Man is, the greater miſeries and hardſhips will he lie expoſed to; for the Senſe of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance will induce him to preſerve his <hi>rightful King</hi> upon the Throne, as far as lawfully he can, and hazard Life and Fortunes in ſo doing, and when he hath done this, he muſt, if he be ſtill obliged to retain <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>true Allegiance</hi> to him, when out of Poſſeſſion, in oppoſition to the <hi>King Regnant,</hi> expoſe his Life and Fortunes ſtill to a greater and more certain hazard. Whereas, as the Seaſonable Diſcourſe well obſerves, <hi>Let Men argue as much as they pleaſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>yet it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that no Man is of ſuch a captivated Allegiance, as by reaſon of it to engage himſelf, or think himſelf engaged to his own certain Ruine and Deſtruction.</hi> The moſt valiant and ſtrictly obliged Troops ſtick not to ask Quarter when they cannot defend themſelves any longer, and are juſtified for it by thoſe to whom they ſwore to bear Faith of Life and Member, as the old Oath of Ligeance did oblige all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Excellent to this purpoſe is that Obſervation of the ſame Author, <q>A Man cannot by Oath, or by any other way, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 41.</note> by natural Allegiance, be obliged further to any Power, than to do his utmoſt in behalf thereof; and though the Oath for the right Magiſtrate be taken in the ſtricteſt terms of bearing Faith or Life, or his natural Allegiance be conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to extend to the venturing the laſt drop of his Blood in his Service; yet it is to be underſtood always with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, if the Action or Paſſion may be for that <hi>Prince</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. For Inſtance, In an Army each man is, or may be obliged by Oath to loſe his Life to the <hi>Prince</hi> whoſe Army it is, rather than turn back, or avoid any danger. This Army, after it hath done its utmoſt, is beaten, and now the Souldiers can do no more for their <hi>Prince</hi> than die, which indeed is to do nothing at all, but to ceaſe from doing any thing either for him or themſelves: In theſe ſtreights therefore, it is not repugnant to their Oaths to ask Quarter, or a new Life, nor to take it with an Obligation of Fidelity to thoſe who give it only upon that condition, or with an Oath never more to fight againſt him who gives it, whilſt his Power continues. In like manner, they who live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the full Power of the <hi>King Regnant</hi> for the time being, may be ſaid to take Quarter for he hath their Lives and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47184:12"/>their Subſtance at his Mercy; and ſo they may as lawfully oblige themſelves to that which the <hi>Prince</hi> in Poſſeſſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires from them; <hi>viz.</hi> that they will live in <hi>Allegiance,</hi> or obedience to him, and will not attempt any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 6. Ibid.</note> The ſame Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> adds, That <hi>this Law wanted not prudence, and deep foreſight; for it did the better take away oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for the People to buſie themſelves to pry into the King's Title; for that, howſoever it fell, their ſafety was already provided for.</hi> And truely, if, as the Author of the Seaſonable Diſcourſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, we may aſſure our ſelves of a juſtifiable Obedience by this, That he who requires it is King in Poſſeſſion, <hi>and hath us, and the means of our Subſiſtence in his Power;</hi> then Subjects may eaſily know the Rule of their Obedience, and the meaneſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity will not be wanting for a Rule of that Subjection to the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> requires, <hi>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> from <hi>Every Soul.</hi> But if all perſons whatſoever muſt be put to the perplexity of examining the Title of every <hi>King</hi> that reigns over them, and is in Poſſeſſion of the Government, it will, I fear, prove a very difficult task, if not impoſſible for <hi>every Soul</hi> to yield this Subjection, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to the preſent Powers, for Conſcience ſake,</hi> or to <hi>every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake;</hi> there being often very intricate perplexities both as to matter of Right, and as to matter of Fact touching theſe things: For, not to inſiſt upon the long Conteſt betwixt the Houſe of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> the meaneſt capacity, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf of the Juſtice of the preſent Cauſe, beſides his general knowledge of the Nature and Obligation of an Oath, muſt be able to paſs an exact Judgment firſt concerning the Deſertion of King <hi>James,</hi> Whether it do not amount to an <hi>Abdication.</hi> Secondly, Whether there were not ſome <hi>Original Contract,</hi> by the Violation of which he may have loſt his Right to govern. Thirdly, whether by his Endeavours to ſubvert the Fundamentals of this Government he may not have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited it. And Fourthly, Whether he may not have done it by actually ſubjecting part of it to a foreign Power; and both it, and himſelf, to <hi>Papal</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Power. Again on the part of King <hi>William,</hi> he muſt know Whether he had not a juſt cauſe of War; and if he had, Whether that do not create a right to the thing gained by it; Whether King <hi>James,</hi> by disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47184:12"/>his Army, and withdrawing his Perſon, did not virtually yield him the Throne: And muſt not the Deciſion of theſe things, if it be neceſſary to be made by every Soul in order to the paying that Obedience to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> he ſtands obliged to yield them for Conſcience ſake, caſt many honeſt Souls into great Mazes, and under inſuperable difficulties? And muſt it not then be very reaſonable to conceive, that God hath given them ſome way more eaſie? And fitted to their mean capacities for ſatisfaction in this caſe; and what can that more likely be, than this of yielding actual Obedience to him whom they find in actual Poſſeſſion of the Government, whilſt they enjoy the benefit of his Protection, and of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, God,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle, hath called us to Peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 7. 1 Cor. vii. 15.</note> i. e. to peace even with <hi>Pagans,</hi> and to a peaceful Deportment in our conjugal and oeconomical Relations; for unto that, he in that <hi>Paragraph</hi> ſeems more immediately to referr:<note place="margin">1 Pet. ij. 12.</note> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> requires the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to yield Subjection to the preſent Powers; that by this good Behaviour their Adverſaries might be convinced of the peaceable Deportment of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and how free their Religion was from cauſing any diſturbance to the Government. Now if <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> did indeed enjoin them to yield this peaceable Subjection to the Powers then reigning, and having full Poſſeſſion of the Government, without a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous enquiry into the juſtneſs of their Titles, they muſt be then obliged to live peaceably under all Governments, and give diſturbance unto none; but if it did enjoin them firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly to enquire, and ſatisfie themſelves of the validity of every <hi>Princes</hi> Title, and refuſe Subjection as oſt as they found reaſon to diſpute the Juſtice of it, it might then often happen, that all of them might be obliged to diſturb the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the <hi>Jewiſh Converts</hi> at that very time, who ſcrupled the Title of any <hi>Heathen Ruler</hi> over them, might lie under continual Temptations to Diſobedience and Tumults. Again, even in our preſent Caſe, if we can bring our ſelves to this perſwaſion, That <hi>Allegiance is due to a King in Poſſeſſion for the time being,</hi> we may not only pray for <hi>all that are in Authority,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. ij. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>that under them we may live peaceable and quiet Lives in all holy Converſation and Godlineſs,</hi> but we ſhall actually do ſo. But if, after the Wiſdom of the <hi>Nation,</hi> in the moſt <hi>ſolemn Aſſembly,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:47184:13"/>hath conferred the Government on ſuch a Perſon, and given him the Title of <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> and put him in full Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Crown,</hi> every private perſon may ſtill not only Queſtion whether they ought to own him as ſuch, but even deny him their Allegiance, and maintain that by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Law of Nature they ſtand bound to give it to another, it is in vain to pray <hi>we may live peaceable and quiet lives</hi> under his Government, to hope for any Settlement of ſuch a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any peaceable ſubſiſtence of it, ſince we conceive our ſelves indiſpenſably obliged to promote, and to abett all ſtruglings to diſturb and overturn it.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>But againſt this Diſcourſe it may be urged,<note place="margin">n. 8. <hi>Obj.</hi>
                     </note> That Allegiance is a Duty we owe unto a lawful Sovereign, not only by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of our Oath, which is ſtiled legal Obedience, but by virtue of the Law of Nature. Now though our legal Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience may ceaſe, as being that which only is impoſed on us by Law, and ſo may be removed by ſuch a Law as render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it impracticable, or transferrs it to another, yet our natural Allegiance muſt be immutable, becauſe the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Law of Nature are ſo. To ſtrengthen this Objection let it be conſidered out of the famous Judgment given in <hi>Calvin</hi>'s <hi>Caſe: Firſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 440.</note> That <hi>our Ligeance is due to our natural Leige Sovereign, deſcended of the blood Royal of the Kings of this Realm.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <q>That by the Law of Nature is the Faith, Lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Obedience of the Subject due to his <hi>Sovereign</hi> or <hi>Superiour,</hi> becauſe Magiſtracy is of Nature; for whatſoever is neceſſary and profitable for the preſervation of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Man, is due by the Law of Nature, but ſo is Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy. Seeing, as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sine imperio nec domus ulla, nec civitas, nec gens, nec hominum univerſum genus ſtare, nec ipſe denique mundus poteſt,</hi> Without Government no Houſe, City, Nation, nor the whole Race of Mankind could ſtand.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <q>That <hi>ſeeing Faith, Obedience and Ligeance are due by the Law of Nature, it followeth that the ſame cannot be changed or taken away.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 441.</note> 
                  <q>That when a Man is out of the <hi>Kings legal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,</hi> as a Man <hi>Out-law'd,</hi> a Man <hi>attainted with a Premunire,</hi> he is not out of his <hi>natural Protection;</hi> but, notwithſtanding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47184:13"/>any Statute, the <hi>King</hi> may protect and pardon him.</q> And ſo, in like manner it ſeems reaſonable to diſtinguiſh betwixt legal and natural Obedience or Allegiance, and to affirm, That by theſe Statutes and Judgments we ſeem to be abſolved indeed from our legal, but cannot by them be abſolved from our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Allegiance. I think I have made the Objection as ſtrong as the moſt ſcrupulous perſon would propound it; and if I can really tender a clear and ſatisfactory Anſwer to it, I hope my foregoing Argument will hold good even in the judgment of the moſt impartial.</p>
               <p>I therefore Anſwer,<note place="margin">n. 9. <hi>Repl.</hi>
                  </note> 1. That what is granted ſeems to yield Advantage enough to us, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>legal Allegiance may ceaſe to be due to a King</hi> de jure, <hi>and may be due to a King</hi> de facto; though natural Allegiance cannot, this laſt is due Antecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all Laws, Promiſes and Oaths, whereas legal Allegiance is that which we by Law do ſwear and promiſe. Natural Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is due to our <hi>natural Liege Lord deſcended of the Royal Blood of the Kings of this Realm.</hi> Legal is that which the Laws exact to the <hi>King</hi> for the time being, though he ſhould not be thus our natural Lord. Natural Allegiance is due becauſe he to whom I owe it is <hi>rightful King.</hi> Legal, becauſe he is <hi>King Regnant,</hi> and actually affords me that protection which calls for Subjection. This is undoubtedly mutable, the other is eſteem'd immutable. Well then, ſuppoſing, but not granting what this Objection doth ſuppoſe, That King <hi>William</hi> were <hi>King</hi> only <hi>de facto,</hi> no natural Allegiance can be due to him, but only legal and mutable; that therefore only is required by the Law impoſing this Oath, and that according to Law is due to him for his legal Protection; Why therefore can we not ſwear to yield him this legal Allegiance, whilſt this Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth continue.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>We cannot, ſay ſome, do it, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                     </label> becauſe it obſtructs the exerting of our natural Allegiance, and ſo obliges us not to perform our Duty, not to yield to the <hi>rightful King</hi> his Right: For inſtance, if a ſtruggle happen betwixt the King <hi>de jure</hi> and <hi>de facto,</hi> it obliges us not to aſſiſt the firſt, as <hi>natural Allegiance,</hi> which never ceaſeth, doth require againſt the latter. Now that is an unlawful Oath which doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us not to perform our Duty.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47184:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>But to this I Anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Repl. </seg>
                  </label> That this Exception makes it as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for a <hi>Conquered Army</hi> to ask <hi>Quarter,</hi> or to receive it upon the Terms forementioned, or for a <hi>Conquered Nation</hi> to ſubmit unto the <hi>Conqueror</hi> until the lineal Succeſſion be extinct; and yet it is generally granted, That in theſe Caſes we may take <hi>Quarter,</hi> and ſubmit upon condition never to ſight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> but to bear Faith and true Allegiance to him. 2. This obſtruction of our <hi>natural Allegiance</hi> is only ſuch as we may reaſonably take for the <hi>preſumptive Will</hi> of the <hi>rightful King,</hi> or that which he ſhould rationally grant to his oppreſſed Subjects; for in extream neceſſity it is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, that he would recede from the Rigour of his Right for Preſervation of his Subjects, rather than by holding them to it, to ſubject them to certain Miſery and Ruine, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving any benefit thereby. We think that the Will of the diſpleaſed Prince is, That he would not have us hopeleſly begin the Miſeries of a new Confuſion for him, we therefore muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Will, that we ſhould not exert our <hi>Natural Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> in ſuch Caſes. Why therefore ſhould it not be as much ſuppoſed his <hi>Preſumptive Will,</hi> that when we cannot refuſe the Promiſe of bearing Faith and true Allegiance to the <hi>King in poſſeſſion for the time being,</hi> without our preſent Miſery and Ruine, we ſhould ſubmit unto it? And therefore it is ſaid, That <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt gave way to the taking the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſe of Engag. <hi>P. 113.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>rather than that his Good Subjects ſhould loſo their Eſtates for refuſing the ſame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 123, 124.</note> And Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the taking of it in this Senſe; <q>I <hi>N. N.</hi> promiſe, That ſo long as I live under this Power and Protection, I will not contrive or attempt any Act of Hoſtility againſt them, but living quietly and peaceably under them, will endeavour my ſelf ſaithfully in my Place and Calling to do what every good Member of a Commonwealth ought to do for the ſafety of my Country.</q> Only he adds this, <q>He who underſtandeth the words of the Engagement,<note place="margin">P. 131.</note> ſo as if they did oblige him to any thing contrary to his Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or render him unable to act according thereunto upon any ſeaſonable emergent occaſion, cannot with a good Conſeience take it, but only he who underſtands it to be no way contrary to his hounden Allegiance ſo long as he is under ſuch a force, and cannot exerciſe it; and that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever that force is removed from him ſo, or he from it,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47184:14"/>as that he hath Power to act according to his Allegiance, the Obligation of the Engagement of it ſelf determines and expires.</q> Now if this be underſtood to be a promiſe to live quietly and peaceably under the Government, without contriving or attempting any act of Hoſtility againſt it, till by the Providence of God it doth expire, or ceaſeth to be the Government under which I am for the time being; then is it the ſame with that Allegiance which the Statute of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> requireth, and theſe Caſes plead for: But if it only be a Promiſe to live quietly under their Government, till they can get an opportunity to deſtroy, and cut their Throats; or an occaſion offers it ſelf to ſide with them that are ſtruggling ſo to do; It is one of the moſt vain, illuſory, ſenſeleſs Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the World, for who knoweth not that, without any Engagements, all men will be quiet till they can get an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to be otherwiſe? Who can have the face to go to any <hi>Prince</hi> with this Petition, Sir, I deſire the benefit of your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and your Government, aſſuring you I will give your Government no Diſturbance till I can get an opportunity to do it, or till I can find ſome Body ſtruggling to Dethrone you? Who can judge it fit that any Government ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch perſons to live in it, who declare themſelves bound, when any opportunity, or ſeaſonable occaſion happens, to endeavour its deſtruction; and when they ſee any body ſtruggling to do ſo, to ſide with them? What are ſuch perſons under the preſent Government, Subjects or Enemies? If the Firſt, then Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> informs them,<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 109.</note> That <hi>Allegiance is ſo intrinſecal, proper, and eſſential a Duty, and as it were fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental to the Relation of a Subject,</hi> qua talis, <hi>as that the very name of a Subject doth after a ſort import it.</hi> If they be Enemies and not Subjects, how can they reaſonably expect that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection which is due only unto Subjects, for that very cauſe that they are <hi>Subjects,</hi> and not that Treatment which all Governments think ſit to uſe to their avowed Enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I Anſwer, That the Reply removes not the whole ſtrength of the Argument, part of it being this,<note place="margin">n. 10. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2.</note> That <hi>Treaſon may be committed againſt a King</hi> de facto <hi>in Poſſeſſion, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be committed againſt a King</hi> de jure <hi>out of Poſſeſſion, and yet it always is committed againſt the natural Allegiance which is due to our Soevereign Lord the King.</hi> And therefore even this natural
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47184:15"/>Allegiance ſeems due to the King in Poſſeſſion, and the exerciſe of it for the time being is Suſpended as to the <hi>King out of Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calv. Caſe. <hi>p. 441.</hi>
                  </note> Moreover our <hi>Law Books,</hi> as they tell us, That the Allegiance of the Subject is due by the Law of Nature; ſo do they alſo tell us, That <hi>Protection and Government is due by the Law of Nature.</hi> What Incongruity therefore is it, that for the time that he cannot perform what is due to the Subject by the Law of Nature,<note place="margin">De jure belli 1. 3. c. 18. § 2.</note> the Subject ſhould ſuſpend the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of what was due to him by the ſame Law. <hi>Grotius</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, That <hi>Reges qui Regnis exuti ſunt, cum aliis Regni bonis, eriam jus leg andi perdiderunt,</hi> That <hi>Kings out of Poſſeſſion of their Kingdoms, have loſt the Right of ſending Ambaſſadors;</hi> and yet that is a natural Right of Kings: And if that, for that time may be loſt to him, and gained to the <hi>King in Poſſeſſion,</hi> Why may it not be ſo as to <hi>Natural Allegiance?</hi> 3. Though our Lawyers diſtinguiſh between <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Legal</hi> Allegiance, yet they do truly tell us,<note place="margin">Calv. Caſe. <hi>p. 435.</hi>
                  </note> That they differ not in Subſtance; but only as the Duty of Allegiance promiſed and ſworn doth: differ from it before thoſe Engagements. <hi>The Subſtance and Effect thereof is due by the Law of Nature, the Form and Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Oath is of humane Proviſion.</hi> So that legal Allegiance contains the Natural, and adds the confirmation of an Oath unto it. Where then the legal Obedience is ſuſpended, and ceaſeth for a time, the natural Obedience muſt much more ceaſe to be exerted.</p>
               <p>Again, the Allegiance which all Subjects owe unto their <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign</hi> is natural, or that which is required of them by the Law of Nature, whether they live under an <hi>abſolute</hi> or <hi>mix'd Monarchy,</hi> under a Government which in no caſe allows them to reſiſt, to take up Arms againſt the <hi>Sovereign;</hi> or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch Governments as that of <hi>Poland,</hi> that of the King of the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See Bodin</hi> 1.2. de Republ c. 5. Grot. de jure belli annot. ad l. 1. c. 4. Sect. 14. Sleid. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, l. 8. p. 195. <hi>See Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 4.</note> and of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and that of the Emperor over the <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Empire;</hi> where, if they violated their Oaths, if they did not preſerve their Laws and Liberties, their very Contract was, <hi>Their Promiſe of Allegiance ſhould go ſor nothing, the Inhabitants of the Kingdom ſhould not be bound to ſhew them any Obedience,</hi> but they ſhould be impowered to reſiſt them, <hi>ſine Rebellionis aut infidelitatis crimine, without the guilt of Rebellion, or breach of Faith.</hi> Whence it is plainly evident, that all natural Allegiance is not immutable and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:47184:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To this Objection I anſwer by Explanation,<note place="margin">n. 11.</note> and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of a natural Right, or a Right grounded on the Law of Nature; and by Application of theſe things to the preſent Subject.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Law of Nature is that which the Dictate of Reaſon, from Principles known, and approved from their own evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, obligeth me to judge ſit to be done, or leſt undone by reaſon of that Moral honeſty or turpitude which is apparent in the Action.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nature may be eſteemed to dictate any thing either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectively, as a thing conſentaneous to the Laws of Reaſon, ſit and agreeable to natural Principles; as perhaps <hi>Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> or <hi>Democracy;</hi> or elſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptively, as neceſſary to be done, or be omitted by virtue of ſome evidence, which clearly ſhews the Equity or Turpitude of the performance or omiſſion of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Of theſe Laws of Nature ſome are Principles, and thoſe either general; as that what is good is to be choſen; what evil is to be avoided, that I am to do; or avoid any thing out of reſpect unto ſome good or evil to my Soul or Body. That which I judge to be fit, due, and meet by the Laws of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Juſtice to be done to me, in the like caſes I muſt do to others; that the publick Good is to be preferr'd before my private Good of the ſame kind.</p>
               <p>Or, ſecondly, relating to Particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> That I ought to do good to all, as far as I can do it without Spiritual, or great Temporal damage to my ſelf. <hi>2dly,</hi> That I am to do no hurt or damage to any innocent perſon, if I can avoid it. <hi>3dly,</hi> That I am to be true to my Word, and faithful to my Promiſe, eſpecially when I have, for the more aſſurance of another, confirmed it with an Oath. <hi>4thly,</hi> That I ought to do my beſt endeavour, that he who hath deſerved well of me, ſhould receive well from me. And againſt theſe Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture God himſelf cannot diſpenſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> he cannot grant liberty to any one to act againſt the Tenor of theſe Laws, even in thoſe circumſtances in which they would have otherwiſe been obliging; and therefore they are truly called immutable, and are the ſame in all who are endowed with the exerciſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Reaſon.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:47184:16"/>
               <p>Some are Concluſions reſulting from theſe Principles, and they do only bind, as we may clearly ſee the natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of them with theſe Principles, and when no Laws of a more ſtrict connexion with them intervene to hinder their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging force.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Some Laws of Nature continually do oblige under all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and ſo their Obligation never ceaſeth; as the Laws forbidding the hatred of God and Idolatry: Others ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige only under ſuch circumſtances; as, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> viz. except when it is neceſſary for thy own preſervation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; Thou ſhalt not take away what is thy Brothers, <hi>viz.</hi> unleſs extream neceſſity compel thee to it. In theſe latter there muſt be a compariſon of Duties, and of Circumſtances, that we may know the better when they are to us Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and when not. Now to apply theſe things.</p>
               <p>It ſeemeth hard to ſay,<note place="margin">n. 12.</note> that by any dictate of Common Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, clear by its own native Light, or any firſt Principle of Nature, we, in theſe circumſtances, are ſtill obliged to yield natural Allegiance to King <hi>James,</hi> and cannot, without viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe Common Principles of cleareſt Reaſon, afford it to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> for then that great <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> thoſe <hi>Reverend Biſhops,</hi> and that numerous <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> which believe they may, and therefore actually have done the contrary, and either have obliged, or exhorted others ſo to do, muſt ſin againſt the cleareſt light of Common Reaſon, which ſure we cannot charitably think or ſay; then muſt this Law of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh,</hi> which hath ſo long obtained, and all thoſe Judgments which have been made ſo ſolemnly by the great <hi>Sages</hi> of the Law, have been Laws made, and Judgments given, and Sentences pronounced againſt the cleareſt light of Nature. Then, thirdly, all perſons of other <hi>Nations,</hi> who in like caſes have done the like in <hi>Swedeland, Portugal,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and other places; and all thoſe learned Perſons, who in their Writings have expreſly, or by juſt conſequence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the transferring of our <hi>Allegiance</hi> in theſe circumſtances, muſt both have acted themſelves, and authorized others to act in contradiction to the plain light of humane Reaſon; which yet ſeems a plain contradiction to that property of a true Law of Nature, that it is the ſame in all who are endowed with the exerciſe of Common Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:47184:16"/>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 13.</note> When it is ſaid that Allegiance from the Subject is due by the Law of Nature to his <hi>Soverign,</hi> this is none of thoſe Laws of Nature which oblige under all Circumſtances: For when I am ſubdued by the Power of another who hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered me, and hath my life at his mercy, no Man doubts but that I may engage, for preſervation of my life, that I will not be active againſt him that gives it; That is, that I will no further bear Allegiance to my former <hi>Sovereign.</hi> When a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or part of it, is ſubdued by a <hi>Conqueror,</hi> without viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hopes of recovering Freedom, they may ſwear Allegiance to the <hi>Conqueror.</hi> 
                  <q>Upon Frontiers, ſaith the <hi>Seaſonable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 47.</note> all Men are moſt ſtrictly obliged to the deſtruction one of another, according to their ſeveral Allegiances; yet it happeneth daily, that by Sieges, and other Extremities, Towns are reduced to the Juriſdiction of thoſe to whom they were ſworn not to ſubmit, but to deſtroy; and upon their Surrender, the muſt ſwear Allegiance to another Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and to deſtroy thoſe whom before they were bound to preſerve; if they afterwards be re-taken by their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Prince,</hi> he cannot look upon them as <hi>Traitors</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters;</hi> for he could neither expect Allegiance from them, when it was impoſſible for them to give it; or the refuſal of Allegiance to the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> when it was impoſſible they ſhould refuſe it without being put to the Sword. The Reaſons which juſtifie ſuch particular places, juſtifie a more univerſal; ſuch as are whole Kingdoms, which are made out of ſuch particular places, and are ſubject to the ſame Fate, and neceſſity of War, to the ſame Confuſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions of Government, and ſo to the ſame oppoſite Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance.</q> This therefore can be only ſuch a Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as binds under ſuch circumſtances, and ceaſeth when thoſe circumſtances ceaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> When Power of Protecting, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Preſerving ceaſe without my fault, and I can have them only from another upon condition of Allegiance.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> Let us conſiderately peruſe the Grounds of natural Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,<note place="margin">n. 14.</note> or the Foundations upon which, according to the learned, it relies; and they, perhaps, may ſomewhat contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute unto our ſatisfaction in this caſe. The foundation of <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Allegiance</hi> is the natural Law of Fidelity, which obligeth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47184:17"/>us to be true unto our Promiſes and Oaths; and this the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection grants may ceaſe. The grounds of natural Allegiance are by our <hi>Judges</hi> in that famous Caſe of <hi>Calvin</hi> declared to be two:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Protection and Government; and from this Ground it is demonſtratively evident, that my natural Allegiance muſt ceaſe to be actually due to him who cannot govern and protect me, and muſt be due to him who actually doth ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> The Neceſſity of Government, and the Profit of it for the preſerving the Society of Man; 'tis neceſſary, becauſe the <hi>Prince</hi> cannot attain the ends of Government, unleſs his Subjects yield him due Obedience; 'tis profitable, becauſe Peace is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and Juſtice hath its due uninterrupted Current, whilſt the <hi>King,</hi> who protects and governs, finds Obedience from his Subjects. Now both theſe Grounds, as hath been ſhewn in <hi>Bagot</hi>'s Caſe, and from the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> require Obedience to the King in Poſſeſſion for the time being; for if there be a neceſſity, when we have loſt our Governor <hi>de jure,</hi> and he is out of Poſſeſſion, that we ſhould ſtill have Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and we cannot have it but from the King <hi>de facto;</hi> there muſt be a neceſſity that we ſhould yield Obedience or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to him; for they are words of the ſame import, and uſed indifferently for the ſame thing in the Old Statute of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance;</hi> the Old Oath being commonly called, ſaith the Act for the abrogation of it,<note place="margin">P. 188.</note> 
                  <hi>The Oath of Allegiance or Obedience.</hi> Peace alſo is preſerved, and Juſtice hath its Courſe under the King in Poſſeſſion, and cannot have its Courſe under him who is out of Poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſe of Engag. <hi>P. 109.</hi>
                  </note> Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Allegiance is a Duty that every Subject by the Law of Nature owes to his Country, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to the Supreme Power thereof; for the ſame Law which we may call the Law of Nature (at leaſt in a large acceptation) which inclineth particular Men to grow into one Civil Body of a Common-wealth, muſt neceſſarily withal imprint a Senſe and tacite acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of ſuch a Duty of Allegiance in every inferior Member of the Body to the Sovereign Power by which the Common-wealth is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, as is neceſſary for the preſervation of the whole Body:</hi> It therefore, ſay I, muſt imprint an acknowledgment of ſuch a Duty of Allegiance in every inferior Member of the Body to the King, <hi>de facto,</hi> in full Poſſeſſion of the Government, becauſe he is <hi>Caput communicatis;</hi> and is, for the time being, that <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47184:17"/>Power</hi> by which the Common-wealth is governed. And this he elſewhere proveth in our very caſe by this cogent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: <q>Whatſoever is to be done for any end,<note place="margin">Lect. 5. de leg. §. 19.</note> is ſo far to be done, as it ſeems neceſſary and profitable for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of that end; but the end of Civil Government, and of the Obedience due to it, is the ſafety and tranquillity of humane Society; and therefore every Subject is bound to obey the Commands of him who, <hi>de facto,</hi> is <hi>Supreme Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor,</hi> as far as the ſafety and tranquillity of that Society requires that Obedience. Now three things are neceſſary for preſerving of humane Society: 1. Defence of our Country againſt Foreign force, and the attempts of her Enemies. [<hi>Add,</hi> And by parity of Reaſon, againſt thoſe who would create Seditions in her bowels; for, ſurely, they are oppoſite to the ſafety and tranquillity of the Society.] <hi>2dly,</hi> The adminiſtration of Juſtice, by which Rewards and Puniſhments may duly be adminiſtred as by Law eſtabliſhed. <hi>3dly,</hi> The care of Trade and Merchandice; for in theſe three things the welfare of Manking doth ſo much conſiſt, that without them all things muſt run to ruin; all places will be filled with Rapines, Murthers, Frauds and Injuries, The Lives and Fortunes of the moſt innocent Subjects will become a prey, to the Luſt of the more powerful; the only, remedy againſt which Evils is, That good Subjects remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that it is their duty to obey their Commands and Laws in all things which relate unto the publick ſafety, by whoſe Sword and Authority they are defended from the injuries of wicked Men.</q> I know he concludes with this exception, That we muſt <hi>ſo yield Obedience to the Invaſor,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">§. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>as not to violate the Right of the Lawful Heir, or do any thing to his prejudice;</hi> Which exception ſhall be conſidered in the following Head.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> Allegiance may be grounded on that Law of Juſtice which enjoins us to give every one his right. But then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Laws, according to that Old Rule, <hi>Protection doth require Allegiance,</hi> according to thoſe known Principles, <hi>That there muſt be always a Government under which the Laws may be preſerved, and Juſtice executed;</hi> and where there is a Government, there muſt be Obedience: I ſay, according to theſe Rules, Allegiance for the time being muſt be the Right
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47184:18"/>of the <hi>King in poſſeſſion for the time being.</hi> Moreover, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things which are in general enjoined by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, humane Laws determine both of the exerciſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of them; for inſtance, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal;</hi> Thou ſhalt not defraud another of his Right, are Laws of Nature; but yet the Law of Man determines what ſhall be eſteemed ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and what defrauding others of their Right. <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> is another Law of Nature; but yet the Law of Man determines when I may kill without committing Murther, and when not; ſo in like manner the Law of Nature requires Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to my <hi>Sovereign;</hi> but for any thing I can ſee to the contrary, the Law of Man may determine who ſhall be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and what is that <hi>Allegiance</hi> I ſtand bound to yield him; and were this otherwiſe, all thoſe Laws fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned of <hi>Poland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 10</note> 
                  <hi>Arragon,</hi> and the <hi>Imperial Princes,</hi> muſt be contrary to the Law of Nature, and to the natural Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance due to their <hi>Soverigns. 3dly.</hi> There can be no prejudice to the Right of the King, <hi>de jure,</hi> in theſe matters in which he doth or ought to be preſumed willing to recede from that Right.<note place="margin">Ibid. Sect. 21.</note> 
                  <q>Now, ſaith the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> it is to be preſumed that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance ſhould be ſo far paid to the Invader, as it ſerves for the good of the Community; the ſafety of which is far more the intereſt of the right Heir, than of him who hath the Poſſeſſion without Right; and ſo this Father of the Country cannot but have that affection for it; that rather than it ſhould be deſtroyed, and his Subjects ruined, they ſhould modeſtly accommodate themſelves to the preſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, than by their unſeaſonable reſiſtance (<hi>add,</hi> or refuſal of Allegiance) they ſhould bring upon themſelves certain deſtruction.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly.</hi> The true foundation of Allegiance is that of the Law of Gratitude, which ſaith, That <hi>from whom I receive Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all the other benefits of Government, to him in gratitude I owe Subjection and Obedience;</hi> and upon this Subjection is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> declaring, That we muſt needs be ſubject, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the Miniſter of God for good.</hi> Now this makes plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Subjection to that <hi>King</hi> from whom, for the time being, we receive Protection, and all the benefits of Government. This is the ground of that Obedience which Children owe unto their <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> to their <hi>Maſters;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47184:18"/>where theſe ceaſe, we may much more ſuppoſe that the Allegiance of Subjects to their <hi>Prince</hi> ſhould ceaſe. Now,</p>
               <p>Though no Man can have the ſame relation to me as my <hi>Father</hi> has, or do that Action which gave him that Relation; yet do the <hi>Roman Laws</hi> conclude, That even <hi>Fathers</hi> may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit this right; ſo far, as that their Childrens obligation to Obedience to them may ceaſe.<note place="margin">Vide Sharock de officiis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae jus, <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 352.</note> The Law of the <hi>Twelve Tables</hi> ſaith, That <hi>if the Father ſell his Son thrice, or his Daughter once, they ſhall be freed from obligation of Obedience to him;</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Imperial Laws,</hi> That <hi>if the Parents will not nouriſh, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Children, they ſhall have no power to recover them to their Obedience,</hi> though by that Action they cannot ceaſe to be their <hi>natural Parents;</hi> That <hi>if Parents ſeek to poiſon, or otherwiſe to attempt the life of their Children, or neglect to take care of them, then ſhall they have no benefit of their Obedience. And as for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, their Law provided thus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 353.</note> That <hi>if ſick Servants were neglected by their Maſters, if, in that ſtate, they caſt them out of their Houſes, neither providing for them themſelves, nor committing them to the care of others, they were to enjoy their liberty.</hi> Now if our Caſe ſhould be determined by the equity of theſe Rules, and I can ſee no reaſon why it may not be ſo; I mean if we do only take our meaſures of it from the Law of Nature, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting from our Oaths, and the deciſion of the <hi>Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures;</hi> that <hi>Father</hi> of the Country who hath deſerted us, caſt off all care of us, expoſed us to the pleaſure of another; that <hi>Maſter</hi> who hath left us when ſick and diſtemper'd, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taking care of us himſelf, nor committing the care of us to any other, muſt have loſt his Title to our Subjection and Obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I anſwer,<note place="margin">n. 15.</note> That in matters of this nature there muſt be place for a compariſon of natural Obligations; and when they ſeem to claſh, thoſe which are more immediate, and neareſt to firſt Principles; thoſe which are moſt obliging un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all circumſtances; thoſe which are moſt immutable, and indiſpenſable, muſt prevail againſt all others which have leſs of theſe great Characters of the Law of Nature inſtamped upon them. Let us then bring this matter to theſe Rules, as Men ſuppoſed to be left purely to the Law of Nature for the deciſion of this caſe, as the Objection doth ſuppoſe, and then it ſeems to be fairly argued,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:47184:19"/>1. That the firſt and moſt immediate Law of Nature is Self-love and Preſervation, as that imports the love and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of my Soul and Body; of my Soul abſolutely, and of my Body by all lawful means, or by ſuch means as are not prejudicial to the higher intereſts of my Soul. This is ſo certainly the fundamental Ground of Action, that I can have no Motive to do any thing, and ſo no Motive to yield Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to any <hi>Sovereign,</hi> which may not be reſolved into theſe Principles; and when theſe Principles combine, and equally affect the whole Society, 'tis their moſt ſtrong and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate bond of Action; according to that known Rule, <hi>ſalus populi eſt ſuprema Lex.</hi> When then the ſafety and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Community depends upon their promiſe of Allegiance to the <hi>Supreme Governor</hi> for the time being, as it muſt do when they are in his Power, and cannot have the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his Protection, and his Government without it; it muſt prevail above all Obligations of Allegiance to him, who, being out of Poſſeſſion, can no more Protect or Govern them.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid that the acting, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> even in this caſe, contrary to their Promiſe and Allegiance, rendring them guilty of falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and perjury, muſt be more prejudicial to their Souls, than their refuſal of Allegiance to the <hi>King Regnant</hi> can be to their Bodies; and ſo it muſt be acting contrary to the true Principle of Preſervation and Self-love.</p>
               <p>I anſwer by Conceſſion, That if thus acting were indeed acting contrary to the true intent and meaning of the Oath of Allegiance; and it were lawful thus to bind our ſelves by Oath and Promiſe; we by thus acting ſhould act againſt Self-love, and the true import of Self-preſervation; but if Men will examine either their own Actions, or the general Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of an Oath, they will find reaſon to believe, that, in ſo doing, they do not indeed act againſt the true intent and meaning of their Oath or Promiſe. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. This Oath of Allegiance, ſay theſe Objectors doth oblige us <hi>to ſpend the laſt drop of our Blood,</hi> and to <hi>hazard our Lives and Fortunes in the King's Service againſt all Men whatſoever;</hi> and yet did any of this Nation, beſides <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves obliged thus to act for King <hi>James</hi> againſt the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> when they ſaw they could not do it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47184:19"/>without being active towards the Ruine of themſelves, their Liberties and their Religion? 'Tis therefore evident, That, by their Actions, they declared they judged themſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted ſo far from that Oath, as it did lay upon them a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of being inſtrumental to promote the Ruine of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Laws and the Religion of the <hi>Nation.</hi> Or doth any Man call a Conquer'd Nation, or a City taken Storm, or a Routed Army, perjured, becauſe they accept of their Lives upon condition of promiſing, upon Oath, allegiance to their <hi>Conqueror?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> The General condition of all Oaths, is, That I will perform them ſo long, and ſo far as it is lawful ſo to do. Now can any Man think it lawful to be active to the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Ruine of himſelf, the Laws, Religion, and Community of which he is a Member. If not, he cannot think himſelf obliged by his Oath or Promiſe to thoſe things which will, in humane probability, have theſe ſad Effects.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> The Oath of Allegiance is a legal Oath impoſed by the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> and <hi>Guardians</hi> of the Community. Now can it reaſonably be thought that they intended to bind the whole Community, and, in them, themſelves to ruine both their Laws, Religion, and their private Intereſts? If not, no Man can rationally think himſelf obliged by ſuch an Oath to do that which apparently doth tend to ſuch an End.</p>
               <p>Again, the immediate Law of all Societies is the publick Good. Now <hi>Allegiance,</hi> ſaith Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſe of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag. <hi>p. 109.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>is a Duty that every Subject owes to his Country, that is, the Publick, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to the Supreme.</hi> And hence it ſeems demonſtratively to follow, that he cannot owe it to the <hi>Supreme Power,</hi> when the performance of it tends plainly, and directly to the ruine of the <hi>publick Good,</hi> and therefore cannot owe it to him, when it tends to the deſtruction of that Community of which he is a Member. The Allegiance which is confirmed by Oath is ſtronger than is <hi>natural Allegiance;</hi> and yet the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> do generally teach, that when the Obſervation of a promiſſory Oath is plainly deſtructive of the publick Good, it is not Obligatory, becauſe the matter of it then becomes unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: For,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:47184:20"/>1. That which we cannot lawfully promiſe, we cannot ſwear to do; but we cannot lawfully Promiſe to be actively Obedient to the Commands of our <hi>Superior</hi> to the ruine of the Publick; we cannot therefore ſwear to be ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An Oath can only bind us to do that which we can be obliged to do; but no Member of a Community can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do what is deſtructive of the Good of the Community, he being,<note place="margin">Jer. xxix. 7.</note> by virtue of his Relation to it, to <hi>ſeek the Peace</hi> and Welfare of it, and <hi>to pray unto the Lord for it;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be obliged to act in contradiction to his Duty, and his Prayers.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> To this Effect may be urged that ſaying of our Lord, <hi>The Sabbath was made for Man;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. ij. 27.</note> that is, for his behoof, <hi>not Man for the Sabbath;</hi> whence he concludes, That the Reſt commanded on that Day, and in which the Obſervation of it did conſiſt, may be violated for the preſervation of Man. Accordingly <hi>Kings</hi> were made for the publick Good, the Welfare and Safety of the Government; and Allegiance, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is therefore due to them, <hi>becauſe they are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God to us for good:</hi> The Community or Publick was not made for them, and conſequently the humane Laws concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and the <hi>Allegiance</hi> we owe to them may be violated, when it is neceſſary to do ſo for the preſervation of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick. When therefore Subjects are under a neceſſity either to Hazard or Ruine the Publick, or to transferr their <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance,</hi> for the time being, to the <hi>King Regnant,</hi> they may do the latter.</p>
               <p>Moreover, it may very probably be argued, That when a King, being wrongfully outed, repairs to a <hi>foreign Power</hi> by which to conquer his own Kingdom, I am not bound by my Allegiance tamely to give up my ſelf, without reſiſtance, to be enſlaved to that power, as I muſt be, if, in ſuch caſes, I may not reſiſt; it being not in the King's Power, how much ſoever it may be in his Will, to Rule or to Command theſe <hi>Conquerors,</hi> and therefore not to hinder our enſlavement to them.</p>
               <p>Yea, when he viſibly attempteth to diſſolve thoſe Laws on the Preſervation of which the Good of the Community con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, or by ſuch evil Methods to ſubject it to <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery, i. e.</hi> to Temporal and Eternal Ruine, my Duty of Allegiance
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47184:20"/>cannot oblige me to be obedient to him in proſecution of thoſe ends. Had I ſworn to ſtay a Priſoner in ſuch a Houſe, that Oath would bind me to ſtay in it, though I found it ſmoaky, and wanting Accommodations for my Health; but not when it is on Fire, or ready to fall down upon my Head, becauſe the Obſervation of it to my own immediate Deſtruction, is againſt the Law of Nature. Much leſs can may Oath of Allegiance bind me to the Subverſion of the Publick, that being more againſt the ſame Law, and the very End of <hi>Societies.</hi> When therefore a King hath put his Conſcience under ſuch Guides as render it morally impoſſible for him to deſiſt from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Eſtabliſhed Religion, and his Power, and Perſon under ſuch Hands, that it is morally impoſſible he ſhould return to his Government without enſlaving the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, and ſubverting her Laws and Liberties, I know not what natural Allegiance, or Principles of meer natural Reaſon can tie me to hazard my own ſafety, by refuſing to promiſe Allegiance for the time being to another who will preſerve both.</p>
               <p>In caſes of ſuch unhappy Conteſts between the good of the <hi>Governor</hi> and the <hi>Governed,</hi> it ſeems moſt natural to think it better, <hi>ut pereat unus, potius quam unitas.</hi> For the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, in ſuch a ſtruggle, may ſuffer much, and yet the Government may not ſuffer, but be as well preſerved in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon. But when a <hi>Kingdom</hi> and a <hi>Church</hi> is thus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and enſlaved, the Government then ſuffers without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Recovery, and the Effects of theſe things reach unto Poſterity. Witneſs the woeful Spectacle of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to the ſuppoſition of the Statute of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh,</hi> and the Caſes cited, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> the King out of Poſſeſſion is <hi>de jure</hi> King, and ſo we muſt be his Subjects <hi>de jure;</hi> theſe being eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Relatives which mutually inferr one of the other. If we be of right his Subjects, we muſt owe him Allegiance of right; and then, How can we promiſe and ſwear to give away his right to another?</p>
               <p>To this Objection I have given a ſufficient Anſwer in what I have Diſcourſed on the Fourth Foundation of Allegiance,<note place="margin">n. 16.</note> the Law of Juſtice. To which things I add, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:47184:21"/>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> That as a King <hi>de jure</hi> hath right to the Allegiance of his Subjects, ſo have they alſo the ſame right to Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Protection by him, and he is by his Coronation Oath obliged to afford it. If then, whilſt he is out of Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the exerciſe of his Government and Protection ceaſeth, though I have a right to it, and he is not to be eſteemed a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olater of his Oath becauſe he doth not then protect us, or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Juſtice for us; Why may not the Exerciſe of that Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which I have promiſed by Oath to him ceaſe, though he hath the ſame right to it?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> When we ſay a King out of Poſſeſſion hath righ tto the Allegiance of his Subjects, we mean not an immediate right, but mediate; <hi>i. e.</hi> our meaning is, That firſt he hath right to Poſſeſſion and actual Government, and by that to Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance; he therefore muſt be firſt in Poſſeſſion, before we can exert the Allegiance due to him. Accordingly, though <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth is by Act of Parliament in the Firſt Year of his eign declared to have been <hi>in Right,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Bagot's <hi>Caſe,</hi> 9 H. 4. Term Trin.</note> 
                  <hi>from the Death of the Right Noble Prince</hi> Richard <hi>Duke of</hi> York, <hi>very juſt King of the Realm of</hi> England; yet becauſe he only took upon him to uſe his Right and Title to the ſaid Realm of <hi>England</hi> on the Fourth of <hi>March, A. D.</hi> 1460. and entered only then <hi>into the Exerciſe of the Royal Eſtate, Dignity, Preheminence and Power of the ſame Crown, and to the Governance of the ſaid Realm of</hi> England, <hi>by the amotion of</hi> Henry <hi>the Sixth</hi> (till then King <hi>in Deed,</hi> though not <hi>of Right;</hi>) therefore is he ſaid by the Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> to have been only <hi>on the Fourth day of</hi> March <hi>in the lawful Poſſeſſion of the ſame Realm, with the Royal Power, Preheminence, Eſtate and Dignity belonging to the Crown thereof;</hi> and then only <hi>to be lawfully ſeized and poſſeſſed of the Crown of</hi> England <hi>in his ſaid Right and Title, and of all Prerogatives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what is only thus of Right, may be both promiſed and performed to another, whilſt this other is in Poſſeſſion, though he be not <hi>de jure</hi> ſo, provided he be ſo according to the Courſe of Law, or the accuſtomed Rights of giving and receiving Poſſeſſion, as is apparent in the Caſe of a <hi>Lord of a Manor,</hi> who is thus in Poſſeſſion of what is the Right of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is by Fraud, or corrupt Verdict, or Judgment, outed of his Right; for the Homage due of Right to the true
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47184:21"/>owner is here, by Law, as occaſion offers it ſelf, to be ſworn to the unjuſt Poſſeſſor. Nay we read of divers Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> continuing the Name and Honour of a King to him, who, by their own Confeſſion, had not the juſt Title, and only proclaiming him who had the right Title, <hi>Heir apparent to the Crown,</hi> as in the very Caſe of<note n="*" place="margin">In ipſa au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vigilia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pta fuit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſio differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae hujuſmodi, <hi>viz.</hi> Quod Dux, &amp; Filii ſui, Edvardus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Marchiae, ac Edmundus Comes Rutlandiae, qui ambo diſcretionis annos attigerant, jurarent ipſi Regi fidelitatem, quodque ipſum recognoſcerent eorum Regem quamdiu ageret in humanis; id enim <hi>Parliamentum ipſum jam decreverat,</hi> addendo, de ipſius Regis conſenſu, quod quamprimum Rex ille in fata diſceſſerit, licebit dicto Duci, ſuiſque Haeredibus, coronam Angliae vendicare, &amp; poſſidere. <hi>Hiſt. Croyl. Ed. Oxon. p.</hi> 550.</note> 
                  <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth; and in the Caſe of<note n="†" place="margin">Theobaldus Cantuarienſis— Utroſque demum ad concordiam emollivit, in tantum quod Rex Juvenem Ducem in filium ſuſceperit adoptivum, &amp; juramenti atteſtatione Regni ſui conſtituit Haeredem, Regi tamen honorem debitum. fidemque, dum viveret, Dux ipſe promiſerat ſe conſervaturum. <hi>Ibid, p.</hi> 451. <hi>Vide Dunelm. continuat. p.</hi> 282.</note> King <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy:</hi> Not to mention the Treaty of Peace made afterwards for the avoiding the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Chriſtian Blood,<note n="‖" place="margin">Daniel<hi>'s Hiſt. pag.</hi> 91.</note> That <hi>Henry the Firſt being inveſted with the Crown, by the Act of the Kingdom, ſhould enjoy the ſame during his Life,</hi> though the juſt Title was in <hi>Robert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Aſſertion,<note place="margin">n. 17. <hi>Obj.</hi> 3.</note> That actual Poſſeſſion makes a <hi>Sovereign Lord the King</hi> for the time being, deſtroys all <hi>Hereditary</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, in which the <hi>Heir</hi> is the power in being without farther Act done by him, or paſſed by the People, or others, and without actual Poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>Since it is certain that no perſon can now claim by a <hi>Paternal Authority</hi> uninterrupted from the beginning, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 'tis certain that all Kingdoms are now <hi>Hereditary</hi> by virtue of their own Conſent and Compact, or by their own Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Crown ſhall be continued in ſuch a Line; it therefore is <hi>Hereditary,</hi> becauſe they have conſented and agreed it ſhould be ſo. If then all Parties concerned have conſented alſo to a Law that a <hi>King,</hi> in quiet Poſſeſſion of this Government, ſhall be looked upon, for th etime being as the <hi>Heir;</hi> that is, ſhall be to all intents and purpoſes, as much <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> as if he were ſo:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cook</hi>'s Inſtit. par. 3. c. 1. p. 7.</note> This Law can bear no Contradiction to ſuch an <hi>Hereditary Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:47184:22"/>but only be a wiſe Proviſion, that in the interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Regular Succeſſion,</hi> Juſtice ſhould never fail, <hi>there being by the Law always a King in whoſe name the Laws are to be maintained and executed;</hi> and therefore they who have the leaſt acquaintance with our <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> muſt know that tho' our Kings <hi>de facto</hi> were more numerous, before the Union of the two Houſes, than thoſe <hi>de jure;</hi> yet are they equally placed in the Catalogue of the <hi>Hereditary</hi> Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and Allegiance was ſworn to them by their ſubjects without any Scruple, as well as to the Kings <hi>de jure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> That the Heir is of Right the Power without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Act done by him, than claiming of the Crown, may be granted; but that he is actually the Power in Being, whilſt he is uncapable, by being out of Poſſeſſion, to exerciſe any Act belonging to the <hi>Supreme Power,</hi> is denied. For we find throughout the whole <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vide <hi>Knighton</hi> Chron. l. 2 c. 5, 8.</note> That they who had the Right by Proximity of Blood, but wanted Poſſeſſion,<note place="margin">See the whole Pedegree of them in <hi>Bagot</hi>'s Caſe <hi>9 Ed. 4. Term. Trin.</hi>
                  </note> were never owned as <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as is viſible in the Caſe of <hi>Robert</hi> the Eldeſt Son of the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> of <hi>Maud</hi> the <hi>Empreſs</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> and <hi>Elenor</hi> his Siſter, and of all the Iſſue of <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence;</hi> who, by the Judgment of the High Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the Eighth of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Heirs Apparent to the Crown, in caſe King <hi>Richard</hi> ſhould die without Iſſue, as he did. On the other hand, they who were Kings <hi>de facto,</hi> and not of Right, as unqueſtionably were King <hi>Stephen</hi> and King <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ed 4. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> c. 1.</note> and as <hi>Henry</hi> IV, V and VI. by Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> were declared to be, were always rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned as true <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and Allegiance was ſworn, and paid to them as ſuch.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Inferior Magiſtrate</hi> is not to be obeyed or owned as our <hi>Superior</hi> in oppoſition to a <hi>Superior Magiſtrate's</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,<note place="margin">n. 18. <hi>Obj.</hi> 4.</note> becauſe in ſuch things he hath no lawful Call, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or Commiſſion; and for the ſame reaſon a King <hi>de facto</hi> is not to be owned, or obeyed as our <hi>Superior</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to a King <hi>de jure,</hi> becauſe he cannot be ſuppoſed to have a lawful Call or Warrant to Exerciſe the Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:47184:22"/>
               <p>If an <hi>Inferior Magiſtrate</hi> hath a Law to warrant his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> he is to obeyed even againſt the verbal commands of his <hi>Superior</hi> without law. Now a King <hi>de facto,</hi> in quiet Poſſeſſion, hath a Law to warrant his Acting as our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and requiring our Faith and true Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance ot him for the time being; he therefore is to be owned and obeyed, as having a legal Call to the Government for the time being.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> To give a ſatisfactory Anſwer to this, and many Objections of the like nature, it will be proper to conſider what a Call, or a Commiſſion to be the <hi>Governor</hi> of any <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> doth import; and for the Reſolution of this Enquiry let it be noted,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God doth not now, as in the Caſe of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> by himſelf appoint and nominate the Perſon who ſhall ſway the Sceptre in any Nation of the World. We ſee by plain Experience God doth not interpoſe in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner in the Election or Conſtitution of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors.</hi> The <hi>Roman Emperors</hi> had no ſuch Appointment, but were Elected by the <hi>roman</hi> Armies, or choſen and confirmed by the <hi>Senate;</hi> whence it muſt follow, That an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Appointment or Deſignation of the Perſon by God, cannot be neceſſary to render any <hi>Prince</hi> God's Ordinance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By virtue of God's general Appointment or Ordinance, that all <hi>Nations</hi> ſhall have ſome Government placed over them, no Individual Perſon can claim a Right to be the <hi>Higher Power</hi> in any <hi>Nation</hi> moe than Others; nor are the People tied to yield Subjection by it to this Man, rather than to that: As then the former Deſignation was more, ſo this is leſs than reaſonably can be required to make a Man the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Perſon</hi> who is God's <hi>Civil Ordinance,</hi> in reference to ſuch a <hi>Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It cannot be ſaid of any Perſon or Family at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the World, That he, or it claimeth, or holdeth the Throne in any Nation by a Right of <hi>Fatherhood</hi> or <hi>Primogeniture</hi> derived from <hi>Adam.</hi> I know no <hi>Prince</hi> on Earth who thus pretendeth to derive his Pedigree, and am perſwaded, that, if any hath the Vanity to make ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant pretence, he cannot thus make out his Title. It remains therefore,</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:47184:23"/>4. That Government be conveyed to this or that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Perſon or Family, by Compact, or Conſent, and Choice of the Perſons governed, that ſuch a Perſon or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily ſhall Exerciſe the Government over ſuch a <hi>Nation,</hi> it therefore muſt be that Choice, Conſent, or Contract of the Perſons to be governed which renders any perſon the Ordinance of God to ſuch a <hi>Nation;</hi> that is, it muſt be granted that all the preſent <hi>Governors</hi> of any <hi>Nation</hi> become <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Ordinance</hi> to them by the Conſent of the Community. Where therefore any perſon is inveſted with the <hi>Supemacy</hi> by them to whom God hath committed the Choice of a <hi>Superior,</hi> or by their conſent to have ſuch Perſons for their <hi>Superiors,</hi> there is the <hi>Ordinance of God.</hi> And if they do admit that perſon to the Government, who by Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and antecedent Compacts hath a right to be ſo, he is to them the <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> de jure. If, in this Choice, they deviate ſubſtantially from theſe Conſtitutions, he only is the <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> de facto; but yet he truly is the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God,</hi> becauſe he is ſo by the only means which God hath left for the Inveſting any Individual Perſon with that Office. Hence do we find throughout the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of our <hi>Kings,</hi> that the Election of, or elſe a Compact with the People, hath generally been looked upon as a thing proper either to ſatisfie the People, or to ſtrengthen their Title to the Crown, thus, <hi>v. g.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the Conqueror,<note place="margin">Dunelm. p. 195. Hoved. par. 1. p. 258.</note> 
                  <hi>Simeon Dunelmenſis</hi> and <hi>Hoveden</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, That <hi>Foedus pepigit, he made a Covenant with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and at his Coronation took an Oath <hi>to defend the Holy Church f God, and the Rectors of the ſame, to govern the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal People Subject to him juſtly, to eſtabliſh equal Laws, and ſee them duly executed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniel, p. 36.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William</hi> the Second held the Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England by the Will of the Kingdom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>the Succeſſion in Right of Primogeniture being none of his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Dan. p. 61. Rich. Huguſt. p. 310.</note> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt was inveſted in the Crown <hi>by the Act of the Kingdom. concilio Communi Baronum Regni Angliae,</hi> ſaith the King.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Stephen</hi> declares himſelf to be choſen King<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſſenſu populi &amp; Cleri in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem electum.</hi> Malmesb. Hiſt. Nov. l. 1. f. 101. b. Rich. Huguſt. p. 314.</note> 
                  <hi>by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People and the clergy,</hi> as he had good reaſon to do, <hi>having no title at all,</hi> ſaith <hi>Daniel, but as one of the Blood, by meer Election advanced to the Crown,</hi> p. 69.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:47184:23"/>
               <p>King <hi>John</hi> received the Crown <hi>by way of Election,</hi> as being choſen <hi>by the States,</hi> ſaith <hi>Daniel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Succeſſion of <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, ſaith<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag. 127.</hi> Non tam jure haereditario quam unanimi aſſenſu proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, <hi>Ed. Franc. 1602. P 95.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Walſingham,</hi> was <hi>not ſo much by Right of Inheritance, as by the unanimous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the peers and Great Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Third was Elected<note n="2" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan. p. 217.</hi> Cui electioni conſenſit popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus univerſus, <hi>id. p. 126.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal conſent of the People,</hi> upon his <hi>Fathers</hi> Reſignation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, on his entrance on the Government, makes a ſolemn declaration<note n="3" place="margin">TRuſſel, p. 179.</note> 
                  <hi>of his Right to the Crown of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>challenging it to belong to him by a double Right; The firſt as Son and Heir to</hi> Richard <hi>Duke of</hi> York, <hi>the Rightful Heir of the ſame; The ſecond, as Elected by Authority of Parliament upon King</hi> Henry<hi>'s forfeit thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh to all his other Titles by<note n="4" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lord</hi> Bac. <hi>Hiſt. of</hi> H. 7. p. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, Conqueſt,</hi> and <hi>from the Houſe of Lancaſter,</hi> adds that of <hi>the Authority of Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Principle makes <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Supreme Power</hi> inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable from Actual Regency,<note place="margin">n. 19. <hi>Obj.</hi> 5.</note> or Command, inveſting him with the <hi>Supreme Power,</hi> who hath it for the time being; and making him incapable of being the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> who is out of Poſſeſſion, whilſt he ſo continues; which ſeems clear contrary to the deciſion of the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> for though <hi>all Iſrael choſe Abſalom to be their King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. xix. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>and anointed him over them,</hi> though he had, for the time, the Kingdom in poſſeſſion; and <hi>David fled out of the Land,</hi> leaving no <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> behind him; yet the Power was in <hi>David,</hi> he was, even then, the <hi>Supreme Governor</hi> and <hi>Higher Power,</hi> to whom Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection was due:<note place="margin">2 Sam. xx. 2. 2 Chr. xxij. 12.</note> So he was alſo when <hi>all Iſrael followed She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba;</hi> And though <hi>Athaliah</hi> poſſeſſed the Kingdom of <hi>Judah</hi> ſix years, <hi>Joaſh</hi> was the true King; and ſo, <hi>the Power ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. This Aſſertion meddles not with the <hi>Right</hi> to, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> but only with the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of the <hi>Supreme Authority.</hi> Now it is plain to Common ſence and experience, that a <hi>King</hi> out of Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, whilſt he ſo continues, cannot do any thing belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Higher Power</hi> to do; nor is he ſuch an <hi>Higher Power</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> repreſents; for he doth not actually <hi>bear the Sword</hi> of Juſtice; he doth not <hi>watch continually for that very thing;</hi> he makes no <hi>Judges</hi> or <hi>Juſtices</hi> of Peace; there are none Commiſſionated by him <hi>for the puniſhment of evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:47184:24"/>or <hi>for the praiſe of them that do well:</hi> He cannot be <hi>a terror unto evil works,</hi> or a Rewarder of the good done in that <hi>Kingdom</hi> in which he hath loſt all Power. So that if it be neceſſary that we ſhould always have a <hi>King</hi> under whom Juſtice ſhould be executed, and the Laws be maintained; and he that is out of Poſſeſſion, for the time being, cannot be that <hi>King;</hi> it plainly ſeems to follow, that for the ſaid time he cannto be <hi>the Miniſter of God to us for Good,</hi> intended by St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, it is as plain that the <hi>King</hi> in quiet poſſeſſion, for the time being, actually doth or may perform all theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and ſo, in reference to them all, may be <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God to us for Good:</hi> And why then may he not be deem'd <hi>the Ordinance of God</hi> for the time being? Or why may not thoſe Laws which make him the <hi>Supreme Power,</hi> and the Executor of theſe Offices for the time being, be alſo ſaid to render him <hi>the Ordinance of God</hi> for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
               <p>The Inſtances produced from the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them parallel to our caſe, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> or opponte to our <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis;</hi> as will be evident, if we conſider, that the Poſſeſſion pleaded for, as being that which creates a Right to our Allegiance for the time being, and renders any Prince <hi>the Ordinance of God</hi> for the ſaid time, is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Full and quiet Poſſeſſion of <hi>Kingly</hi> Government, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Conteſt of any oppoſite <hi>prince</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Nation;</hi> for he who is not <hi>King,</hi> can never be <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> Poſſeſſion given and received by the uſual method, <hi>viz.</hi> The Conſent of all the Repreſentatives of the People Governed, and the Coronation of the Perſon Governing, with the uſual engagements to the Governed. Which Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, how unneceſſary ſoever it may be to a <hi>Prince</hi> who hath an <hi>Hereditary</hi> Title to the Crown, muſt neceſſarily be needful to make a <hi>King,</hi> who is not ſo by Birth-right, <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King</hi> for the time being.</p>
               <p>For want of theſe two things, though <hi>Oliver</hi> had engroſſed the whole Government, yet was he ſtill a <hi>meer <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> and no legal Governor; and therefore no Allegiance could, by our Laws, be due unto him, he being no <hi>King,</hi> much leſs a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47184:24"/>
                  <hi>King</hi> choſen by the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> and Crowned in the uſual manner. And by the enjoyment of theſe things it was that King <hi>Stephen, John,</hi> and the three <hi>Henrys,</hi> though deficient in Title by Birth-right, were notwithſtanding, in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective times, <hi>our Kings,</hi> and ſo <hi>the Odinance of God</hi> for the ſaid time. This being premiſed, the impertinency of all the inſtances produced, will eaſily appear. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. As for <hi>Abſalom,</hi> he never had any qiet poſſeſſion of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> nor did ever <hi>David</hi> flee out of the Land; for when the Battel was fought, he was in <hi>Mahanaim,</hi> a City of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and a <hi>Sacerdotal City;</hi> He had with him an Army of his own Subjects able to cope with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> beſides thoſe who in reality were for <hi>David,</hi> though they pretended to follow <hi>Abſalom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly, Sheba</hi> was never Anointed, or placed on the Throne; he never had Poſſeſſion, or any deliberate Conſent of the <hi>ten Tribes;</hi> for he was preſently purſued,<note place="margin">2 Sam. xx. 14.</note> not only by the Men of <hi>Judah,</hi> but of <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> That <hi>Athaliah</hi> ever ruled by the conſent and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the People of <hi>Judah,</hi> is not evident from the Sacred <hi>Records;</hi> perhaps ſhe did it only by meer force and violence,<note place="margin">2 Chr. xxij 9. xxiij. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe the houſe of Ahaziah had no power to keep ſtill the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> or becauſe they knew of noen of the <hi>Seed-Royal</hi> that ſurvived.</p>
               <p>Moreover, in all theſe inſtances there was an expreſs Law or Declaration of the Will of God againſt all theſe pretenders: For <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Sheba</hi> rebelled againſt that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> whom the Lord had expreſly choſen <hi>to ſeed Jacob his Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. lxxviij. 71.</note> 
                  <hi>and Iſrael his Inheritance: Athaliah</hi> was excluded by that Declaration, Promiſe, Oath of God, whereby he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged that <hi>David's Kingdom ſhould be eſtabliſhed for ever,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. lxxxix. 33, 34, 35. 2 Sam. vij. 16.</note> and that <hi>there ſhould not want a man to ſit upon his Throne.</hi> Whence having found a Son of <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>People</hi> with one voice cry out, <hi>The King's Son ſhall Reign,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chr. xxiij. 3</note> 
                  <hi>as the Lord hath ſaid of the Sons of David.</hi> Now though 'tis granted that no man can be <hi>God's Ordinance</hi> againſt his own immediate and expreſs Appointment of another individual perſon ſo to be; this hinders not, but where there is a Law to make it ſo, where the ſame ways are uſed which convey a good Title, and where the exerciſe of the Government is conveyed by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47184:25"/>them whom God hath intruſted with the deſignation of the <hi>Individual Governor;</hi> that <hi>Governor</hi> may exerciſe the Supreme Power for the time being, even when the Right is in another, or may at leaſt be deemed God's Ordinance in ſo doing.</p>
               <p>For whereas it is ſaid that <hi>Civil Magiſtracy</hi> is by the Law of Nature; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> but he that is only King <hi>de facto,</hi> and ſo is <hi>King</hi> in prejudice to, and violation of anothers Right, cannot be a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> by the Law of Nature, but againſt it; and ſo his exerciſe of that <hi>Authority</hi> is contrary to the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>I Anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Repl. </seg>
                  </label> that <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> is only by the Law of Nature, becauſe ſome government is ſo; not becauſe this <hi>Individual Governor</hi> is ſo. If therefore Government may equally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed under a King <hi>de facto,</hi> as <hi>de jure;</hi> they may be equally by the Law of Nature, becauſe thoſe Acts of Government, <hi>viz.</hi> the puniſhing Offenders, the protecting of the Innocent, and whatſoever elſe is of the Law of Nature; becauſe eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Government which is ſo, may equally be performed by both.</p>
               <p>For a Concluſion of this Anſwer, and this Section with it, it may deſerve to be conſidered, That in theſe and all other caſes of ſuch <hi>Popular Elections,</hi> and <hi>Revolts</hi> left on Record in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> we find not any perſon puniſhed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as Rebels for ſiding with the oppoſite Party againſt their Rightful <hi>King;</hi> None that followed <hi>Adonijah,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed him <hi>King;</hi> none of the ten Tribes who Anointed <hi>Abſalom,</hi> or followed after <hi>Sheba;</hi> none who ſubmitted to <hi>Athaliah.</hi> To which add a like Obſervation out of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In the Life of <hi>Hen. 3. p. 181.</hi>
                  </note> viz. <hi>It is worthy the Note, that we find no execution of blood, except in open battel, in all theſe combuſtions; nor any Nobleman to die on a Scaffold, either in this King's Reign, or any other, ſince</hi> William <hi>the Firſt, which is now almoſt Three hundred years.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:47184:25"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>NOW as the ſtrength of this Argument ſeems to me greater than is that of many others which are produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in this Cauſe, ſo are there many ſingular advantages which it hath above them. For inſtance:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whereas, 'tis ſaid,<note place="margin">n. 1.</note> That we cannot take this Oath upon the Grounds which commonly are offered to move us ſo to do, without condemning the Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> allowing Subjects, in ſome caſes, a Power to Depoſe their Prince; aſſerting, that our Allegiance to him may ceaſe even whilſt he doth continue to Govern, or to ſway the Sceptre; and ſo we cannot, upon thoſe Motives, comply with the Act enjoining us to take it, without condemning our ancient and avowed Doctrines, our Subſcriptions to our <hi>Homilies</hi> and <hi>Canons,</hi> if not the Doctrine of the <hi>Ancient Church,</hi> and that which once was counted the Glory of the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and conſequently we cannot do it on thoſe Principles, without the ſcandal of Hypocriſie and Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability; and ſo of being <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Weathercocks,</hi> that turn with every wind that blows; and Men of ſuch flexible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, as will permit us to ſwear backwards and forwards, or any ways for our intereſt; which ſcandal would cauſe ur Perſons to be deſpiſed, and our Doctrine not to be regarded. Whereas, I ſay, ſome of the other Grounds of taking the Oath of Fealty and Allegiance to King <hi>William</hi> ſeem to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject us to theſe and many other inconveniencies, this way entirely avoids them all. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We may ſtill honeſtly declare, as do our <hi>Statutes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 2. 3. Jam. 1. c. 1. Can. 36.60. Can. 1. 1640.</note> our <hi>Canons,</hi> and our <hi>Convocations,</hi> That <hi>the King's Highneſs is the only Supreme Governor of this Realm, and of all other his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Countries;</hi> That <hi>the Kingly Authority within his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Countries is immediately, and after</hi> God, <hi>Chief and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme; and that all Subjects by divine Law ſtand bound to yield all Faith and Obedience to it above all Earthly Power whatſoever.</hi> For this Doctrine doth not in the leaſt diminiſh any Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47184:26"/>or meddle with any Prerogatives of <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> but only tells us who, for the time being, is that <hi>Sovereign Lord</hi> to whom theſe <hi>Prerogatives</hi> belong.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">n. 3.</note> We may ſtill honeſtly declare, That <hi>it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever to take up Arms againſt the King;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stat. Car. 2 A. 14. cap. 2.12. Car. 2. cap. 10.</note> And that <hi>by the undoubted fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, neither the Peers of this Realm, nor the Commons, nor both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Parliament, nor the People collectively or repreſentatively, nor any other perſons whatſoever had, have, hath, or ought to have any coercive Power over the Kings of this Realm.</hi> And with our Convocation ſtill aſſert,<note place="margin">A. D. 1640. Can. 1.</note> That <hi>for Subjects to bear Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their King, offenſive or defenſive, upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, is at the leaſt to reſiſt the Powers which are ordained of God.</hi> We may ſtill ſubſcribe theſe Doctrines of our <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> as <hi>wholſome and godly Doctrines, and Doctrines to be embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by all men;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2d Par. of the Serm. of Obed. <hi>p. 72.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>it is not lawful for Subjects and Inferiors in any caſe to reſiſt and ſtand againſt Superior Powers; that Chriſt hath taught us plainly, that even the wicked Rulers have their Power and Authority from God; and therefore it is not lawful for their Subjects to withſtand them, <hi>Although they do abuſe their Power;</hi>
                  </hi> That <hi>if they would command us to do any thing contrary to God's Commandments, in that caſe we may not in any wiſe withſtand them violently,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 74, 75.</note> 
                  <hi>or rebel againſt Rulers, or make any Inſurrection, Sedition or Tumults, either by force of Arms or otherwiſe, <hi>Againſt the Anointed of the Lord, or any of his Officers,</hi> but we muſt in ſuch caſe patiently ſuffer <hi>all wrongs and injuries,</hi> referring the Judgment of our Cauſe only to God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hem. of Rebel. <hi>Par. 2. p. 301.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>And that though Multitudes, not only of the Rude and Raſcal Commons, but ſometimes alſo Men of great Wit, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and Authority, have moved Rebellions againſt their lawful Princes (whereas true Nobility ſhould moſt abhor ſuch villanies,) though they ſhould pretend ſundry Cauſes; as the Redreſs of the Common-wealth (which Rebellion, of all other miſchiefs, doth moſt deſtroy,) or Reformation of Religion (whereas Rebellion is moſt of all againſt true Religion,) yet were the multitude of the Rebels ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great, the Captains never ſo noble, politick, and witty, the pretences feigned to be never ſo good and holy; yet the ſpeedy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of all Rebels, of what number, ſtate, or condition ſoever they were, or what colour and cauſe ſoever they pretend, is, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47184:26"/>ever hath been ſuch, that God thereby doth ſhew, that <hi>He allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neither the dignity of any perſon, nor the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of any people, nor the weight of any cauſe as ſufficient,</hi> for the which Subjects may move Rebellion againſt their Prince.</hi> For this Doctrine only adds to theſe Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars this, That the <hi>King Regnant in poſſeſſion</hi> is the <hi>King</hi> whom we may <hi>not reſiſt in any caſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. We are not obliged for the juſtification of our ſelves,<note place="margin">n. 4.</note> and of our Doctrine, to appeal from the <hi>Homilies</hi> themſelves, to thoſe who compoſed or ſubſcribed them, to prove their Actions towards others, and the Sayings of one or two of them elſewhere, were inconſiſtent with the plain import of the words which they ſubſcribed and taught as <hi>good and wholſome Doctrine,</hi> when it ſerved to defend the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> againſt the Inſurrections of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> the chief Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of that Doctrine which <hi>England</hi> knew of in thoſe times; or to inſinuate, to their diſparagement, that they held this to be good Doctrine, when it was uſeful to ſecure them againſt the <hi>Romaniſts;</hi> but that the Doctrine of the Lawfulneſs of Reſiſtance was as good when it was uſeful to preſerve the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or beyond the Seas, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Romaniſts:</hi> But can fairly account for that aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which they gave to their oppreſſed <hi>Brethren</hi> from the difference betwixt the conſtitution of their Government, and ours; this being one of the chief Laws by which the liberty of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> was long maintained and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any Prince hath diſturbed the State of the Republick either by violence, wrong dealing, or treachery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oration of the Lawfulneſs of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh</hi> War, <hi>p. 14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>then all the States and Burghers may deny him Obedience, and ſhall be free, and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of their Oaths; they ſhall appoint a Chief in his place, until he be reduced to a better Mind, and more eaſie Government.</hi> From the Obſervation of Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> out of <hi>Bodinus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. 2. de Rep. c. 5.</note> That in <hi>France, Spain, England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> Reges ſine controverſia jura Majeſtatis habent per ſe: ſingulis civibus, nec univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis fas eſt ſummi principis vitam, famam aut fortunas in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimen vocare, ſive vi, ſive judicio conſtituto id fiat; <hi>Their Kings have all the Rights of Majeſty within themſelves; and 'tis not lawful for any of, or all their Subjects to bring their Lives,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47184:27"/>Fame, or Fortunes into jeopardy, either by force, or way of juſtice. But as for the Emperor of Germany,</hi> Charles <hi>the Fifth,</hi> Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nide cives ad Rempublicam oppreſſit, cum jura Majeſtatis non haberet;<note place="margin">Divin. Dial. par. 2. p. 81.</note> 
                  <hi>He, by his Tyranny over his Subjects, when he had not the Rights of Majeſty, forced them to reſolve themſelves into a Common-wealth.</hi> And from that of Dr. <hi>More,</hi> That<note n="*" place="margin">Lutherus ſemper docuerat, Magiſtratui non eſſe reſi ſtendum, &amp; extabat ejus de hac re libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus; cum autem in hac delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione periti juris docerent legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eſſe permiſſum reſiſtere non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunquam, &amp; nunc in eum (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum de quo leges inter alia men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem faciant, rem eſſe dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam oſtenderent, Lutherus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuè profitetur ſe neſciviſſe hoc licere. <hi>Sleid. Comment. l.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 195.</note> 
                  <hi>Luther would never aſſent to the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy of defenſive Wars at</hi> Smalcald, <hi>till he was throughly inſtructed by the learned in the Law touching the Conſtitution of the Empire of</hi> Germany, <hi>that by the</hi> Magna Charta <hi>of that Empire the Princes of the Empire are inveſted with ſuch Rights, as if they be violated by the Emperor; it is lawful for them to take Arms and reſiſt,</hi> Sine Rebellionis, &amp; inſidelitatis crimine, <hi>Without the Crime of Rebellion and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſs; and that the Emperor had vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated thoſe Rights:</hi> Much leſs are we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to fly to ſuch Aſſertions as theſe, <hi>viz. The Homilies of Obedience do <hi>no where</hi> teach Submiſſion to lawleſs Violence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. J. <hi>p.</hi> 73.</note> 
                  <hi>but only to lawful Authority; and the Homilies againſt Rebellin ſpeak not one word of ſubmitting to mauthoritative or lawleſs Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. of Obed. <hi>Par. 2. p. 72.</hi> of Reb. <hi>p. 277.</hi>
                  </note> Whence it muſt follow, that <hi>Princes</hi> have lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to <hi>be ſharp and rigorous, and wrong doers; to abuſe their power;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 74, 75. <hi>Hom. of Rebel.</hi> p. 287, 288.</note> 
                  <hi>to do all wrongs and injuries to them who will not obey them againſt God's Commandments; to be mortal Enemies, ſeeking the Lives of their Subjects; to be naughty, cruel Princes; Princes that be to their good Subjects mortal Enemies; Princes that are hurtful, or like to be hurtful to the Common-wealth:</hi> For whoſoever reads thoſe <hi>Homilies</hi> honeſtly and carefully, will find in them almoſt as many Paſſages as Pages requiring Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to ſuch <hi>Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">n. 5.</note> We may ſtill with our <hi>Forefathers</hi> condemn thoſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Doctrines</hi> which aſcribe unto the <hi>Pope</hi> a power of crub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the depoſing <hi>Princes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Biſh. <hi>Morton's</hi> diſcovery of the Rom. Doctrine in the Caſe of Conſpiracy and Rebellion, <hi>p 9, 15, 19, 37.</hi>
                  </note> in caſe of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> perverting of Faith, and perſecution of their <hi>Catholick Subjects,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it lawful for <hi>Catholioks</hi> to break Faith with <hi>Hereticks;</hi> to do evil that good may come; to uſe fraud, falſhood, and injuſtice, treachery, and diſſimulation, for the benefit
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47184:27"/>of holy <hi>Church;</hi> we may, as they have done before us, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe Principles as Rebellious, which ſet up a Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical or Monarchical Power of People, or of Pope over <hi>Princes;</hi> which diſſolve the Oath of Obedience to <hi>Princes;</hi> which countenance the violating Faith with men of divers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions; which allow the Doctrine of forcible Depoſing of <hi>Princes</hi> from their Thrones. I ſay, We may ſtill do all this without fear of having that of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> retorted on us; <hi>Thou art inexcuſable, O Man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. ij. 1, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſoever thou art that judgeſt: for wherein thou judgest another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf; for thou that judgeſt, doſt the ſame things. And thinkeſt thou this, O Man, that judgeſt them who do ſuch things, and doſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment of God.</hi> For we by taking of the Oath of Fidelity and Allegiance to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> upon this Principle, approve of no <hi>Democratical</hi> Power over our <hi>Sovereign Lord the King:</hi> No forcible depoſing of <hi>Princes</hi> from their Thrones; but, without farther enquiry after their Right, if we find them ſetled by the Naitons <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in quiet Poſſeſſion of the Throne, give them <hi>Faith,</hi> and that <hi>Allegiance</hi> which our Laws have made due to every <hi>King</hi> in the Poſſeſſion of the Realm. And laſtly, we allow of no other Abſolution from our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Oaths than that which <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> of all Perſwaſions do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of; <hi>viz. By the Ceſſation of the matter of our Oath,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> now ceaſing to be <hi>King in Poſſeſſion,</hi> and ſo in the Law Sence, to be our <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 6.</note> We may alſo retain our old Sence and Expoſition of St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter, viz.</hi> That the preſent Powers which by the Law are ſuch, be they ſuch as duly uſe, or do abuſe the Power committed to them; ſuch as, according to their Duty, are <hi>the Miniſters of God for good:</hi> Or, ſuch as prove eventually the Encouragers of evil Doers, are ſtill the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God; and therefore he that doth reſiſt them ſhall receive to himſelf Damnation, and are not by our Principles obliged to reſtrain their words unto ſuch <hi>Princes</hi> as are in <hi>Fact</hi> as well as <hi>Duty, the Miniſters of God for good;</hi> but only to ſuch <hi>Princes,</hi> as, by the Tenor of our Law, become <hi>our Sovereign Lords,</hi> however they demean themſelves in the Exerciſe of the Government; and ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:47184:28"/>we are not concerned in theſe Objections againſt the other Interpretation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it rather ſeems to make the Diſcourſe of theſe <hi>Apoſtles</hi> an Exemption from Subjection and Obedience to the then preſent Powers, and an allowance to them, than any Obligation to be ſubject and obedient to them, they being not in <hi>Fact</hi> as well as <hi>Duty</hi> the <hi>Miniſters of God for good;</hi> but moſt unnaturally and barbarouſly Cruel, of a moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage, bloody Temper, as is recorded in the <hi>Roman Hiſtories</hi> touching <hi>Tiberius, Claudius, Caligula</hi> and <hi>Nero;</hi> or if ſuch perſons were to be obeyed without Reſiſtance, as being the Miniſters of God for good, who then may be reſiſted for not being ſo?</p>
               <p n="2">2. It plainly ſeems to lay upon the Bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles</hi> the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Diſſimulation, and acting not according to that Simplicity and Plainneſs as might have reaſonably been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the Diſcpenſers of the Goſpel; for without any limitation or exception, they require every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Soul <hi>to be ſubject to the Higher Powers for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and, upon pain of Damnation, never to reſiſt them: They declared to the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, That <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> required all its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, how ill ſoever they were treated, how cruelly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they were perſecuted, how wrongfully ſoever they did ſuffer from them, to ſuffer with the greateſt patience, and never to take up the Sword for their Defence againſt them, but after the Example of their Lord, when they thus ſuffer, not to revile and threaten, and much leſs to reſiſt their <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors,</hi> but only <hi>to commit their Cauſe to him that judgeth Righteouſly.</hi> Now if, after all theſe Declarations, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed allowed all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to reſiſt and take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>Governors,</hi> when they conceived them guilty of Tyrannical abuſe of Power; when they became <hi>a terror to good Works,</hi> and not to Evil only; when they did not act according to Juſtice, or eſtabliſhed Laws, or for the Good and Welfare of the Kingdom, but the contrary; ſurely they cannot be excuſed from a ſemblance of Deceit, and of impoſing on the <hi>Heathen</hi> World.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It plainly ſeems to make them guilty of the Murther of thoſe many <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who, when they declared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47184:28"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Vide <hi>Tertull.</hi> Ap. c. 37. ad Scap. c. 5. <hi>Cypr.</hi> Ep. ad Deme. r. <hi>Buſeb.</hi> l. 8. c. 1, 4. <hi>Auſt.</hi> de Civ. Dei l. 22. c. 6.</note> ſufficient both for ſtrength and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to reſiſt and overcome their Perſecutors, at the ſame time declared, they durſt not do it, becauſe it was forbidden by the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Laws.</p>
               <p>And whereas againſt our Interpretation of the words it may be objected,<note place="margin">n. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> That it makes wicked Magiſtrates the Miniſters of God to us for good, the Powers ordained of God; yea, that according to it, even <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> if they can once ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain quiet Poſſeſſion, and the conſent of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and of the <hi>Commons,</hi> muſt alſo be <hi>the Ordinance of God</hi> for the time being.</p>
               <p>This I confeſs is true; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> but then it ſeemeth to be only that which <hi>Scripture,</hi> which <hi>Antiquity,</hi> which Reaſon, and the Law of this our Nation doth allow and juſtifie. For of thoſe wicked <hi>Enperors</hi> forementioned, it is that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, They are <hi>the Miniſters of God to thee for good;</hi> to them it is St. <hi>Peter</hi> doth require Subjection,<note place="margin">1 Pet. ij. 14.</note> as to men <hi>ſent for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well.</hi> And even of the Power of <hi>Pilate</hi> to condemn our <hi>Saviour, Christ</hi> doth himſelf confeſs, That it was <hi>given</hi> him <hi>from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. xix. 11.</note> And Reaſon ſaith the ſame; for, even under wicked <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> Juſtice is executed, Offenders againſt the Lives and Lively-hoods of others puniſhed, and Peace preſerved; and from their Government it is that we are kept from the Inſolencies of Thieves and Robbers, from barbarous Aſſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinations, and all the miſeries of Anarchy. For, <hi>take away the Higher Powers,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, and all goes to wreck,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſ. in Rom. Hom 23. Tom. 3. p. 191.</note> 
                  <hi>neither will City, nor Country, nor Family, nor Aſſembly, nor ought elſe ſtand, the ſtronger will devour the weaker, and all things will be turned upſide down.</hi> So that we do in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure receive that good from the moſt wicked and depraved <hi>Governors,</hi> which without Government we could not have. Accordingly the <hi>ancient Chriſtians</hi> ſay in General of thoſe Kings who were not very good, at leaſt many of them, in their times, That they are <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> That by his command <hi>Kings are Ordained,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theoph. ad Autol. l. 1. p. 76.</note> That they were <hi>appointed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47184:29"/>by God,</hi> That <hi>they received their Government from above;</hi> That <hi>the Emperor derives his Government from him from whom he doth receive his breath;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iren. l. 5. c. 24. Tertull. Apol. c. 30, 33. ad Scap. c. 2.</note> That <hi>he is the Man whom God chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and therefore muſt be loved by Chriſtians, who know he is appointed by God,</hi> and that <hi>he makes them Governors over the Nations.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Legat. pro Chriſtianis. Apud Euſ. H. Eccl. l. 7. c. 11. Apud Athanaſ. Ep. ad Solit. Vit. agentes.</note> 
                  <hi>Athenagoras</hi> ſaith of <hi>Aurelius</hi> and <hi>Commodus, You have received the Kingdom from above. Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> of <hi>Valerianus</hi> and <hi>Gallienus, God hath committed the Kingdom to you. Hoſius</hi> of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who laboured might and main to introduce the <hi>Arian Hereſie</hi> into the <hi>Church,</hi> againſt thoſe <hi>Imperial</hi> Laws which had eſtabliſhed the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> Faith, That <hi>God had given to him the Empire. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> of <hi>Trier, Lucifer</hi> of <hi>Calaris, Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Vercelli,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Millain,</hi> That <hi>God gave to him the Kingdom. Athanaſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apol. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. De Civ. Dei l. 5. c. 21.</note> That <hi>God by his Word had given the Kingdom to his Servant</hi> Conſtantius. <hi>He that gave the Government to</hi> Marius, ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, gave it to</hi> Caeſar; <hi>he who gave it to</hi> Auguſtus, <hi>gave it alſo to</hi> Nero; <hi>he who gave it to the</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſians <hi>most ſweet Emperors, gave it alſo to the most cruel</hi> Domitian; <hi>and he who gave it to that most Chriſtian Prince</hi> Cnſtantine, <hi>gave it to</hi> Julian <hi>the Apoſtate. Tho he be wicked, abominably wicked; though he commit Ten thouſand Evils, and do the worſt of miſchiefs to us,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, yet he is a King, a Governor, one to whom the Government is committed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be reverenced, and not to be deſpiſed for his wickedneſs, but revered for his Dignity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet it may be ſaid,<note place="margin">n. 8.</note> How true ſoever this may be of an evil King, who hath a lawful Title to his Government, it ſeems ſtrange and incongruous to aſſert, That he who is only King <hi>de facto,</hi> and ſo can only Exerciſe that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which doth of Right belong unto another, ſhould be <hi>the Ordinance of God;</hi> and it is liable to theſe great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections and Abſurdities.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> 
                  <q>That which renders a man an Uſurper of another Man's Right, without due Title or Admiſſion to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Right, can never render him the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God to which I owe Subjection and Allegiance; but that which makes him only King <hi>de facto,</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to a King <hi>de jure,</hi> makes him an Uſurper of another
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:47184:29"/>Man's Right, without due Title or Admiſſion to the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that Right.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> 
                  <q>The Precept: <hi>Let every Soul be Subject to the Higher Powers</hi> cannot agree to him who is only King <hi>de facto</hi> in oppoſition to him that is King <hi>de jure;</hi> for this Subjection doth not only ſignifie a Paſſive Obedience, or <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> but an active Execution and Obſervation of all his lawful Commands, the Contribution of Taxes, to his Support and Maintenance, our Aſſiſtance and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to keep him in his Station by our Arms, Purſe; our Counſel and our Prayers; our Love, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Honour of him: In a word, our Fidelity and Allegiance to him againſt all others. Now can all this be due to a King <hi>de facto</hi> in oppoſition to him whoſe Right it is.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> 
                  <q>It is Damnation to reſiſt the Power ordained of God in favour of any other perſon; but can it be Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to reſiſt him who is only King <hi>de facto,</hi> in Favour of a King <hi>de jure,</hi> to whom aſſiſtance muſt be due <hi>de jure?</hi> If ſo, then what juſt War can he made for the Recovery of his Right? or, why did <hi>Jehoiada</hi> not only Depoſe, but cauſe <hi>Athaliah</hi> to be Murthered for the ſake of <hi>Joaſh?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> 
                  <q>The Power is <hi>the Miniſter of God,</hi> or one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated and Deputed by him, for the ſame Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance that a Subordinate <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> hath upon his <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign</hi> for becoming <hi>his Miniſter,</hi> the ſame hath a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Magiſtrate</hi> upon God for being <hi>his Miniſter;</hi> but can any one be Deputed or Commiſſionated by God to take away another Man's Right, or wrongfully to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it?</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly.</hi> 
                  <q>By this Aſſertion no King <hi>de facto,</hi> or in quiet poſſeſſion can be an unjuſt Poſſeſſor, or an unlawful occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant of the Throne; for he that is ſo in, as to be God's Ordinance; <hi>i. e.</hi> Commiſſionated and Deputed by him to be the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> muſt needs be rightly in, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to execute the Government.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe,<note place="margin">n. 9.</note> I confeſs, ſeem to be great Abſurdities at the firſt view, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> and ſuch as plainly ſhock the whole Foundation of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47184:30"/>our Argument; but yet, I hope, their force may be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently abated by theſe Conſiderations following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That ſome of theſe Arguments ſeem with an equal ſtrength to prove, that wicked <hi>Kings</hi> are not, and cannot be the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> or, <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> as that <hi>Kings</hi> in poſſeſſion without Right, can never be ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it is plain to common Senſe, and the Experience of Men, that a <hi>King out of Poſſeſſion,</hi> whilſt he is ſo, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth none of the <hi>Characters</hi> and Offices aſcribed by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> and that the King <hi>de facto</hi> doth, or may exerciſe them all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That he who in our Caſe is <hi>King Regnant in Poeſſeſſion</hi> is not to be deemed an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> in the Law Sence and Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Word.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That by the difference which muſt be put betwixt him and a meer <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> all the forementioned Objections may be ſolved. And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Some of theſe Arguments ſeem with an equal ſtrength to prove what moſt undoubtedly is falſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Princes</hi> acting wrongfully and injuriouſly towards their Subjects can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the <hi>Higher Powers;</hi> for it is certain they can derive no power from God, but for the good of Man. They can have no Commiſſion, Title or Authority from him to hurt the Innocent, to pervert Judgment, or to do Evil to his People; they therefore do exert this Power without due Title or Commiſſion from God, they uſurp upon the Rights of other Men; for every Subject has a right to Juſtice, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry innocent perſon to Protection from ſuffering hurt or violence. They cannot be Commiſſionated or Deputed by God to do theſe things; for then they muſt have Authority from God to do them, and ſo they muſt be rightly done: And yet even in theſe Caſes we muſt <hi>ſuffer patiently,</hi> and be thus ſubject <hi>for Conſcience towards God,</hi> and cannot forcibly reſiſt them without the peril of Damnation, which we only can incurr, becauſe we do reſiſt the <hi>Higher Powers.</hi> They therefore in theſe Actions are at once the Power, and the Abuſers of the Power, yea the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> of a Power which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to them; and therefore even of the Power of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> to condemn the bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> our Lord ſpeaks thus: <hi>Thou couldſt have no Power over me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. xix. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>unleſs it were given thee
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47184:30"/>from above.</hi> And when <hi>Peter</hi> drew his Sword in the defence of his Innocence againſt men Commiſſionated by an <hi>Illegal High Prieſt,</hi> he ſaith unto him,<note place="margin">Mat. xxvi. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>Put up thy Sword into its place, for all that take the Sword ſhall periſh by it.</hi> Moreover, if Subjection ſignifies active Subjection to their Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Government, if it require our Arms, Purſe, Counſels, Prayers, 'tis certain this cannot lawfully be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to ſtrengthen and aſſiſt them in theſe Evil Actions; but that, in all theſe Caſes, we may both Counſel, and pray againſt their Wickedneſs, and though we may not even then lift up our hands againſt them, we may hold them down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">n. 17.</note> In Anſwer to the Fifth Objection in the Second Section I have proved, that it is plain to common Sence, that a King out of Poſſeſſion, whilſt he is ſo, cannot do any thing belonging to the <hi>Higher Powers</hi> to do, and that a King <hi>de facto</hi> in Poſſeſſion may perform all things of that Nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I add, That King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> being <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> by the conſent of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the Kingdom, cannot be looked upon as meer <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> for the Reaſon given in <hi>Bagot</hi>'s Caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Sixth,</hi> That <hi>he was not to be deemed an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, becauſe the Crown had been entailed on him by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi> Which may be proved,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the nature of a meer Uſurper or Poſſeſſor,<note place="margin">Gre. <hi>p.</hi> 295.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>That <hi>he is one who is in the place of Power without any Call, Conſent, or Conſtitution of the People; or, that he is one that is in meerly by his own Act:</hi>
                  </q> Whereas King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> are not in the place of Power meerly by their own Acts, but by the Call, Conſent, and Conſtitution of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and People.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From the Nature and the Eſſentials of Government. For what doth conſtitute it but the Subjection of the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Party, or the Reſignation of themſelves, their wills, abilities or powers to the Rule and Arbitration of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? What Title hath any <hi>Conqueror</hi> to another Man's Subjects without this? Or what <hi>King</hi> now in Being can claim a Right unto his Kingdom upon any other Title? What are the motives to Government but the preſervation of Peace and Order, and the prevention of Injuries and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47184:31"/>Wrongs? When then there is, after mature deliberation had, ſuch an actual Deſignation of the whole Community, there is Government conveyed in that very way in which it always was, ſince paternal Government ceaſed, communicated; and in which alone it can be properly conveyed: And ſo, there is no Uſurpation of it in reſpect of him who thus receives it, whatever irregularities may be in their Actions who do thus conferr it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I add, That by due obſervation of the difference which muſt be put betwixt Uſurpers, and our preſent <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen;</hi> and the two Obſervations made, all the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Objections may be ſolved. For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> As we compared them before with the Caſe of a <hi>King</hi> injurious to his Subjects, and found them almoſt as ſtrong againſt his being the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> ſo let us again compare them with the Caſe of a <hi>King</hi> injurious to his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>King,</hi> injuſtly Invading, and ſo entirely Conquering his Dominions, and ſeizing on them for himſelf. Did not the beginning of this Action conſtitute him an injurious Perſon, when he takes upon him the Government thus got? doth he not take away another Man's Right? and muſt he not then wrongfully detain it? is not the perſon, thus wrongfully Excluded, King <hi>de jure?</hi> may he not juſtly wage War for the Recovery of his Right? but yet do not all Perſons own that 'tis not only lawful, but even neceſſary for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, after ſuch Conqueſt, to conſent to take the <hi>Conqueror</hi> for their <hi>Governor,</hi> to yield Allegiance to him; and that by doing ſo, they render him the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> and the <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God?</hi> And yet all the forementioned Objections are as ſtrong againſt him, as any other unjuſt Poſſeſſor of the Throne.</p>
               <p>Moreover, by a particular conſideration of them, it will be evident, that they partly have received a ſufficient An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and that 'tis eaſie from the Premiſes, to give a full Solution to them. To reaſſume them therefore in their order, it is Objected,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>That which renders a Man an Uſurper of another Man's Right,<note place="margin">n. 10. <hi>Obj.</hi> 1.</note> without due Title or Admiſſion to the Exerciſe of that Right, can never render him the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47184:31"/>of God, to which I owe Subjection and Allegiance; but that which maketh any perſon King <hi>de facto</hi> only, in oppoſition to a King <hi>de jure,</hi> maketh himan Uſurper of another Man's right without due Title or Admiſſion to the exerciſe of that Right, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer, That a due Title may be either ſuch, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Repl. </seg>
                  </label> as, according to the ſtrict Rules of Juſtice bears that name, as being obtained by due means, and conferr'd without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice or injury done to any perſon; and ſo it muſt be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that a King <hi>de facto,</hi> or an unjuſt <hi>Conqueror</hi> can have no due Title againſt a King <hi>de jure:</hi> Or, <hi>2dly,</hi> that may be ſtiled a due Title which is legal, or allowed of by the Law, and which is conferr'd with thoſe Formalities of Law, and with thoſe uſual Ceremonies and Rites which cuſtomarily are obſerved in the moſt Regular Collations of thoſe Titles. A Title juſt, in the firſt ſence, cannot be neceſſary to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Prince</hi> the Ordinance of God, or any other <hi>Secular</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> perſon capable of being owned as ſuch; for then none of the <hi>jewiſh High Prieſts,</hi> in the times of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> could have been owned as <hi>God's Ordinance,</hi> they having ſeldom obtained that Office by due means; nor having it conferr'd upon them without the injury of him, to whom by God's direction it belonged for life, viz. <hi>The eldeſt Son of the houſe of Aaron;</hi> for the <hi>Procurator</hi> of <hi>Judea</hi> made that Office <hi>Annual;</hi> it was uſually bought and ſold:<note place="margin">Vide Ham. in Luc. 3. not c.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſephus</hi> reckons no leſs than twenty eight of theſe irregular Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to that Dignity; and yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> owns one of theſe very perſons as <hi>the Ruler of the People:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. xxiij. 5.</note> Our Lord owns thoſe who were ſent by their Authority as men who <hi>could not be reſiſted lawfully.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. xxvj. 52. Joh. xi. 49, 51.</note> The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth own them as <hi>High Prieſts,</hi> and even aſſiſted one of the worſt of them to <hi>prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> whilſt he held the Office: Nor doth our <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his Right unto that Title. Moreover, thoſe <hi>Biſhops</hi> which received their Power and Inveſtiture from thoſe <hi>Popes</hi> who wreſted it from <hi>Kings,</hi> and others who had right to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and to elect them, could not, upon this ſuppoſition, be <hi>God's Ordinance,</hi> nor as ſuch obeyed in prejudice to the Rights of <hi>kings,</hi> and theſe <hi>Electors. 3dly,</hi> No <hi>Conqueror</hi> of a Rightful <hi>king</hi> could be God's Ordinance, notwithſtanding
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:47184:32"/>any conſent afterwards obtained from the People. <hi>4thly,</hi> The four great <hi>Monarohies</hi> could not be <hi>the Ordinance of God</hi> with reſpect to the greateſt part of their Dominions, which they obtained only by the Sword. <hi>5thly,</hi> Moſt of the <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors</hi> in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Times could not be truly ſtiled God's Ordinance, as being advanced to the <hi>Imperial</hi> Throne, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Arbitrary choice of the <hi>Army,</hi> than the free An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent choice of the <hi>Senate.</hi> Then, <hi>laſtly,</hi> had we of this Nation no Ordinance of God in being, during the Reigns of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth, Fifth,</hi> and <hi>Sixth,</hi> that is, for the ſpace of ſixty years, they being accounted, and in one of our Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> often ſtiled Kings <hi>in Deed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4.</note> and not <hi>of Right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if a due Title, in the Second ſence, be ſufficient to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a perſon the Ordinance of God; then, be it ſuppoſed, though not granted, that King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> are only King and Queen <hi>de facto,</hi> yet may they have a due Title, becauſe they have a legal Title from thoſe Laws which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> for the time being, to be our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns within the parvien of the Statute.</hi> The Government alſo being conferr'd upon them by conſent of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> repreſenting all the Coverned, they being Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> after the uſual manner; and ſo having the Government conferr'd upon them with thoſe Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Law, and with thoſe uſual Ceremonies and Rites which cuſtomarily are obſerved in Collating of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Precept;<note place="margin">n. 11. <hi>Obj.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> cannot agree to him who is only King <hi>de facto,</hi> in oppoſition to him who is King <hi>de jure;</hi> for this Subjection doth not only ſignifie a paſſive Obedience, or Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but an active Execution and Obſervation of all his lawful Commands; the Contribution of Taxes to his ſupport and maintenance; our Aſſiſtance and Endeavours to keep him in his Station by our Arms, Purſe; our Counſel and our Prayers; our Love, Reverence, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Flim: In a word, our Fidelity and Allegiance to Him againſt all others.</q> Now can all this be due to a King <hi>de facto,</hi> in oppoſition to him whoſe Right it is?</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:47184:32"/>1. Our Law ſeems very plainly to require moſt of this to a King <hi>de facto,</hi> for the time being; as making it our duty, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> to do him <hi>true and faithful Service and Allegiance,</hi> and that becauſe, for the time being, he is <hi>our Sovereign Lord the King,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> to which we are to be ſubject for the time being; and if he may be <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> as I have ſhewed he is, moſt of the things here ſaid to be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Subjection, muſt be due unto him by St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2hly,</hi> I have ſhew'd already, that a King out of Poſſeſſion, while he continues ſo to be, cannot do any thing required by the Office of the <hi>Higher Power;</hi> he cannot <hi>bear the Sword</hi> of Juſtice; he can Commiſſion none to <hi>puniſh evil doers,</hi> or reward the Good; he cannot be <hi>the Miniſter of God to us for good:</hi> And yet it is on theſe accounts that St. <hi>Paul</hi> lays a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Subjection on us, <hi>Not only for Wrath, but Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake;</hi> and that he tells us we are <hi>to pay tribute,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>continually attending on theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have alſo ſhew'd, that from a King, <hi>de facto,</hi> in full and peaceable Poſſeſſion of the Government, we do or may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all theſe benefits, and in all theſe particulars; He may be unto us <hi>the Miniſter of God for good,</hi> and that from Him alone it is we can receive actual Protection, and all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Government, (if therefore it be neceſſary that we ſhould always have a <hi>King</hi> under whom Juſtice ſhould be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and the Laws have their courſe, it ſeems as neceſſary that the <hi>King,</hi> for the time being, ſhould be received as our <hi>King;</hi> if Protection doth require Allegiance, and we, for the time being, do receive it only from him, it ſeems as evident, that for the time being, we ſhould yield it only to Him.) If then the King, <hi>de jure,</hi> out of Poſſeſſion, can be to no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes <hi>the Miniſter of God to us for good,</hi> and the King, <hi>de facto,</hi> may be ſo to all the ſaid intents and purpoſes; then may he alſo be the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> and the <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> for the time being. In a word, the <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice Coke</hi> expreſly ſaith,<note place="margin">Inſtit. par. 3. p. 7.</note> That <hi>by the Law there is always a King in whoſe name the Laws are to be maintained and executed, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Juſtice ſhould fail;</hi> and if ſo, then by the Law the <hi>King Regnant</hi> muſt be our <hi>King,</hi> there being no other in whoſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47184:33"/>name the Laws can be maintained and executed, and the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure of Juſtice be prevented: And if he be the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> he muſt alſo be that <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> for the time being, to which we owe the Duties mentioned in the Objection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> As for the firſt of theſe Duties, <hi>An active execution and obſervation of all the lawful Commands of the King Regnant for the time being,</hi> it admits no real Ground of Scruple; for lawful Commands may lawfully be obeyed.</p>
               <p>The Contribution of <hi>Taxes</hi> to his ſupport and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is by St. <hi>Paul</hi> declared to be due, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for this very cauſe;</hi> that <hi>he attends continually upon the Government,</hi> and therefore due to him that doth ſo.</p>
               <p>Our Aſſiſtance to promote the welfare of the Government we are under, by our Prayers and Counſels, ſeems plainly to be our duty by virtue of that Command which God gave to his own People, and the continuance of the Reaſon of it; <hi>Seek the peace of the City,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. xxix. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>whither I have cauſed you to be carried away Captives, and pray unto the Lord for it; for in the peace thereof you ſhall have peace;</hi> and of that <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Injunction, That <hi>prayers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. ij. 1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſupplications, interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all that are in Authority, or eminent Place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for our endeavours to keep them in their Station by our Arms, it only can be ſo far our duty as it is lawful ſo to do: Nor do I find St. <hi>Paul</hi> inculcating it as any part of our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the <hi>Higher Powers;</hi> nor doth our Law, ſince the Ceſſation of the Tenure of Knights. Service require it perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of all Subjects. At leaſt we of the <hi>Clergy</hi> cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it, becauſe we by ſo many Statutes are exempted from bearing Arms.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>laſtly,</hi> as for <hi>bearing Faith and true Allegiance,</hi> you ſee our Law doth plainly and expreſly make it due unto a King <hi>de facto.</hi> And ſo I cannot fee why all theſe Duties may not, as far as we can be concerned in them, be paid to ſuch a King for the time being.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It is damnation to reſiſt the Power ordained of God in favour of any other perſon;<note place="margin">n. 12. <hi>Obj.</hi> 3.</note> but can it be damnation to reſiſt him who is only King <hi>de facto,</hi> in favour of a King <hi>de jure?</hi> if 2o, then what juſt War can be made for the Recovery of his Right? or why did <hi>Jehoiada</hi> not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:47184:33"/>but even cauſe <hi>Athaliah</hi> to be murthered for the ſake of <hi>Joaſh.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The word which we tranſlate <hi>Damnation,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is <hi>Judgment.</hi> Now, by our Law, Treaſon may be committed againſt a King <hi>de facto,</hi> and that is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by the Judgment of Death; and if this Treaſon be an offence againſt the natural Allegiance due to the King <hi>de facto,</hi> as all Treaſons are, and I do thus offend <hi>by levying War againſt the King for the time being, in this Realm, by being adherent to his Enemies, or giving Aid unto them,</hi> I muſt be guilty of it by doing this in favour of a King <hi>de jure.</hi> It therefore may be judgment to reſiſt the King <hi>de facto,</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the King <hi>de jure,</hi> i. e. it may be an Offence which, by the Law, will render me obnoxious to judgment. If the King <hi>de jure,</hi> at his return to exerciſe the Government, may puniſh me for any Treaſonable action done againſt the King <hi>de facto,</hi> and conſequently for reſiſting ſuch a King in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of himſelf, it muſt be an Offence deſerving Judgment, according to our Law, thus to reſiſt the King <hi>de facto,</hi> in favour of the King <hi>de jure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor doth it follow hence, that the King <hi>de jure,</hi> can make no juſt War for the Recovery of his Right; for this he may do by the Aſſiſtance of his Allies, by Foreign Aids, or by thoſe Subjects who have ſtill adhered to him, or will repair unto him; only they cannot do it who have received Protection, and lived for a time in quiet ſubjection to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Government. If therefore Men will act up to their principle, That <hi>their Allegiance is ſtill due to King</hi> James, they muſt immediately go out of the Realm, and repair thither where they alone can pay it to him. If they think it unlawful to own any Allegiance due to King <hi>William,</hi> they muſt expect no Protection, ſeek for no Juſtice from him, pay no Taxes to him; for if they repair to him, as the <hi>Avenger</hi> of any evil done to them, or as <hi>the Miniſter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;</hi> if they pay him any Taxes, they thereby virtually own him as the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> ſeeing theſe things are only due unto him, and can be expected from him, becauſe he is the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> and you are his <hi>Subjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:47184:34"/>
               <p>To the Caſe of <hi>Athaliah</hi> I have Anſwered before;<note place="margin">§. 2. n. 17.</note> and ſhall now only add, That if ſhe obtained any conſent from the People, it was by reaſon of their ignorance that ſhe had any Competitor, or that any of the Sons of <hi>Ahaziah</hi> were alive; and that ſhe could not have the Throne of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> whilſt any of the <hi>Seed-Royal</hi> lived, by reaſon of God's manifeſt declaration to the contrary; and therefore when the King's Son was diſcovered, <hi>the Prieſts, the Levites, and the Chief of Iſrael</hi> do preſently cry out,<note place="margin">2 Chr. xxiij. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the King's Son ſhall Reign, as the Lord hath ſaid of the houſe of David:</hi> Here therefore was the immediate Declaration, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and the Oath of God againſt her; which whoſoever in our caſe can ſhew, will make this inſtance pertinent. Moreover, ſhe who gained conſent only on ſuppoſition, that there was none of that Seed of <hi>David</hi> left, of whom God had expreſly ſaid, That they <hi>ſhould ſit upon the Throne,</hi> could only be ſuppoſed to have their conſent ſo long as no ſuch Seed appeared.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Power is the Miniſter of God,<note place="margin">n. 13. <hi>Obj.</hi> 4.</note> or one commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and Deputed by him, for the ſame dependance that a Subordinate Magiſtrate hath upon his Sovereign for becoming his Miniſter; the ſame hath a Sovereign Prince upon God for being his Miniſter: But can any one be Deputed or Commiſſionated by God to take away another Man's right, or wrongfully to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it?</q>
               </p>
               <p>That the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrate</hi> is Commiſſionated by God to be his Miniſter, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> as well as the Inferior Officer is to be the <hi>Prince</hi>'s Miniſter, is true; but there is a ſignal difference as to the manner of conveying this Commiſſion; for the Inferior Officer is perſonally named by ſome of his <hi>Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors,</hi> and acts by virtue of a particular Grant or Inſtrument of his <hi>Superior</hi> conveying that Office to him, or impoſing it upon him by name; whereas ſince the times of the <hi>Jewiſh Kings,</hi> no man can pretend any ſuch Title to be the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power</hi> in any Kingdom; God never perſonally naming
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47184:34"/>now, or immediately declaring the Perſon who is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in any Kingdom, but leaving this to be done by the governed, according to Prudential Rules, or according to the Conſtitutions they have made among themſelves; here therefore may be great fault committed by the Governed, in varying from the form of Government preſcribed by their Conſtitutions, or from the Perſon they by thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions were obliged to admit unto the Government; and yet the Perſon they do pitch upon to Govern after ſuch a form may be <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> as being pitched upon by them to whom his Providence thought fit to leave the management of this affair; and though their irregular Proceedings can juſtifie no man in taking or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining what is another Man's right, eſpecially if he in conſcience be convinced that it is ſo; yet may it render him <hi>the Ordinance of God</hi> who exerciſeth the Government thus devolved upon him, becauſe he is the Miniſter of God by the ſame way and method by which the juſteſt Title is conferr'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>By this Aſſertion no King, <hi>de facto,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">n. 14. <hi>Obj.</hi> 5.</note> thus put in quiet poſſeſſion of the Government, can be an unjuſt Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, or an unlawful Occupant of the Throne; for he that is ſo in as to be God's Ordinance, that is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated and Deputed by him to be the Higher Power, muſt needs be rightly in, and Authorized to exerciſe the Government.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He that is ſo God's Ordinance as to be immediately Deputed by him, as <hi>Saul, David, Solomon,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> can never be an unjuſt Poſſeſſor; but he who is only the Ordinance of God mediately, and by virtue of ſuch and ſuch Acts done by the Governed to make him ſo, may be an unjuſt Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor as oft as they conferr the Government upon him in oppoſition to another, to whom in juſtice, or by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of their Government they ſhould have given it.</p>
               <p>Again, He may be ſtiled an unlawful Occupant of the Throne, with reference to them, who, againſt the Tenor
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47184:35"/>of their Laws and Conſtitutions, did conferr it on him; but cannot be ſtiled an unlawful Occupant, as that importeth one, who by Law cannot exerciſe the Government con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on him; becauſe the Law doth make him for the time being our <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and one to whom true Duty and Service of Allegiance is to be tendered by his Subjects. Thus he, who by an unjuſt Decree of a corrupt Judge, or the falſe Teſtimony of a Witneſs, not then diſcerned ſo to be, gets the Poſſeſſion of, and becomes Lord of a Manor, is an unjuſt Poſſeſſor, but not an unlawful Occupant, becauſe he hath obtained it by form of Law; and the Tenants are obliged, whilſt he continues in Poſſeſſion, to ſwear Homage to him, as there is occaſion, as much as they did formerly to him who juſtly was poſſeſſed of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>6thly.</hi> Moreover, we are not by our Principles obliged to condemn the <hi>ancient Chriſtians,</hi> not only as Fools and ſelf-Murtherers, but introducers of <hi>a miſchievous Turkiſh Doctrine,</hi> even <hi>the ſlaviſh Doctrine of the Bow-ſtring;</hi> but may, with <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Contr. Celſ. l. 3. p. 115.</note> continue to aſſert, That <hi>the mild Laws of Chriſtianity are ſuch by which they are obliged to ſuffer themſelves to be ſlain, rather than to avenge themſelves upon their Perſecutors, of what kind ſoever;</hi> and may believe the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Martyrs,</hi> to be never the worſe <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> becauſe they ſaid,<note place="margin">Nos enim nos ipſos tanquam oves tradidimus ad occiſionem, ut qui didicerimus eſſe ſubjecti omnibus poteſtatibus. <hi>Apud</hi> uſher, <hi>Power of the Prince,</hi> p. 223.</note> 
                  <hi>We have given up our ſelves as Sheep to the ſlaughter, having learne to be ſubject to every Ordinance of Man.</hi> We may ſtill judge it was for the Praiſe, and not the Condemnation of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that <hi>Origen</hi> declared, That, after all the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and unjuſt Severities the <hi>Emperors</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ibid.</note> they could give <hi>no example of any Sedition of the Chriſtians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Circa Majeſtatem Imperatoris defamamur, ſed nunquam Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biniani, vel Nigriani vel Caſſiani inveniri potuerunt Chriſtiani. Ad <hi>Scap. c.</hi> 2. Erant de Romanis non Chriſtianis, <hi>Apol. c.</hi> 30.</note> That <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian's Apology</hi> for them runs thus, <hi>No Chriſtian was ever found a Rebel: As for</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenninus Niger, <hi>and</hi> Clodius Albinus <hi>who rebelled againſt</hi> Severus; <hi>and</hi> Caſſius, <hi>who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt</hi> Verus; <hi>they were</hi> Romans, <hi>but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47184:35"/>none of them Chriſtians.</hi> Though the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Ael. Spartian. in Vita Severi p. 347, 349, 353.</note> That the Emperor <hi>Severus</hi> was a Man truly anſwering his Name, <hi>and of infinite Cruelty, not only to the meaner ſort, but to the Senators.</hi> That Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Neque tunc Civitas Chrlſti—quamvis haberet magnorum ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina populorum adverſus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pios perſecutores ſuos pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porali ſalute pugnavit, ſed po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, ut obtineret aeternam, non repugnavit. <hi>De Civ. Dei l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> That <hi>the City of Chriſt, though it had Armies of great People appertaining to it, did not fight for their temporal ſafety againſt their cruel Perſecutors, but rather, that it might obtain eternal happineſs, made no reſiſtance at all.</hi> And we may ſtill think it no diſparagement to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that they accounted the <hi>Thebaean Legion</hi> true <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and <hi>compoſed Hymns to be ſung in praiſe of them Day and Night.</hi> Nor need we have a worſe Opinion of that which anciently was ſtiled, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Orig. Contr. Celſ. l. 8. p. 426, 427.</note> 
                  <hi>The Divine Aid, the whole Armor of God, the Host of Piety.</hi> And by Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> is called,<note place="margin">Pugnabimus uſque ad mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſi ita oportuerit, pro ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre noſtra <hi>ARMIS Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S LICET,</hi> non ſcutis &amp; gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis, ſed precibus, fletibuſque ad Deum. <hi>Ep.</hi> 221. ad Ludovic. Regem.</note> 
                  <hi>The Weapons with which alone it is lawful for us to fight againſt our Prince;</hi> becauſe this hath been lately rendered <hi>the miſchievous Cant of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Tears;</hi> for our Principles oblige us to reſiſt none, to be patient under, and ſubmiſſive to all <hi>Higher Powers</hi> for the Lord's ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>7thly.</hi> Again, our Principles give no encouragement to any to rebel againſt, or call their <hi>Princes</hi> to an account for Arbitrary Government, or violation of their <hi>Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Oaths;</hi> but, whatſoever they may be to us, require our Subjection and Allegiance to them, and our ſincere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, by all lawful means (though not by being active to the Ruine of the <hi>Church</hi> and State) whilſt they are in poſſeſſion of the Government to keep them there. For as the Statute of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> ſaith, That <hi>no perſon or perſons ſhall take any benefit or advantage by this Act, which ſhall hereafter decline from his, or their ſaid Allegiance:</hi> So can they, from our Doctrine, have no advantage ſo to do.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:47184:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Our <hi>Principles</hi> do not concern themſelves either with the ſuppoſed Title of the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> or the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed defect of Title in King <hi>William;</hi> for do but grant what is plain matter of Fact, that neither King <hi>James,</hi> nor the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> are in Poſſeſſion of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and that King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> are in Poſſeſſion of it by the conſent and approbation of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Faith and true Allegiance</hi> for the time being, muſt, by our Principles, be due unto the latter, whatſoever Right or Title may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the former.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 18. line 16. for <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> read <hi>diſplaced:</hi> p. 31. l. 32. dele <hi>of:</hi> p. 46. l. 5. add <hi>reſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:47184:36"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>Awnſham Churchill</hi> at the Black Swan at <hi>Amen-Corner.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Late Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Caſe, with Obſervations upon it. Written by the Right Honourable <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>De la Mere. fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Hiſtorical Account of Making the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and by the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> againſt the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Wherein the true <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Laws</hi> is given, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> moſt barbarous Uſage of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> under a Colour of <hi>Law,</hi> ſet forth; and the <hi>Reformation</hi> Vindicated from the Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of being <hi>Cruel</hi> and <hi>Bloody,</hi> unjuſtly caſt upon it by thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh Communion.</hi> By <hi>Samuel Blackerby,</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſter of <hi>Grays-Inn. fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obedience Due to the Preſent King, notwithſtanding our Oaths to the Former. Written by a Divine of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A modeſt Enquiry, Whether St. <hi>Peter</hi> were ever at <hi>Rome,</hi> and Biſhop of that <hi>Church?</hi> wherein, I. The Arguments of Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others, for the Affirmative, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. II. Some Conſiderations taken Notice of, that render the Negative higſtly Probable. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit of <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Politick Maxims</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. laid open to the World. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Memorials of the Method and Manner of Proceedings in Parliament in Paſſing Bills. Together with ſeveral Rules and Cuſtoms, which by long and conſtant Practice have obtained the Name of <hi>Orders of the Houſe.</hi> Gathered by Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and out of the Journal Books, from the time of <hi>Edward</hi> VI. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Tracts in Two Volumes. <hi>Vol.</hi> I. Containing, 1. His Travels into <hi>Switzerland, Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> with an Appendix. 2. Animadverſions on the Reflections upon the Travels. 3. Three Letters of the <hi>Quietiſts, Inquiſuion,</hi> and State of <hi>Italy. Vol.</hi> II. 4. His Tranſlations of <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> of the Death of Perſecutors. 5. His Anſwers to Mr. <hi>Varillas:</hi> In Three Parts. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Texts of Scripture, with ſhort Notes upon them. And ſome other Obſervations againſt the Principal <hi>Popiſh Errors.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47184:37"/>
            <p>The Fallibility of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, Demonſtrated from the manifeſt Error of the Second <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Trent</hi> Councils, which Aſſert, <hi>That the Veneration and Honorary Worſhip of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, is a Tradition Primitive and Apoſtolical.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Demonſtration that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils have Erred; by ſhewing, That the Councils of <hi>Conſtance, Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> have, in all their Decrees touching Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in one Kind, contradicted the Received Doctrine of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> with an <hi>Appendix,</hi> in Anſwer to the XXI. Chapter of the Author of <hi>A Papiſt Miſrepreſented, and Repreſented.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of <hi>Traditions,</hi> Part I. Wherein it is proved, That we have Evidence ſufficient from <hi>Tradition;</hi> 1. That the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> are the Word of God. 2. That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> owns the true Canon of the Books of the <hi>Old Teſtament.</hi> 3. That the <hi>Copies</hi> of the <hi>Scripture</hi> have not been corrupted. 4. That the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have no ſuch Evidence for their <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi> 5. That the Teſtimony of the preſent <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> can be no ſure Evidence of <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition.</hi> 6. What <hi>Traditions</hi> may ſecurely be relied upon, and what not. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of <hi>Traditions,</hi> Part II. Shewing the Novelty of the pretended <hi>traditions</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> as being, 1. Not mentioned by the <hi>Ancients</hi> of their Diſcourſes of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions Apoſtolical,</hi> truly ſo called, or ſo eſteemed by them. Nor, 2. In their Avowed <hi>Rule,</hi> or <hi>Symbol</hi> of Faith. Nor, 3. In the Inſtructions given to the <hi>Clergy,</hi> concerning all thoſe things they were to teach the People. Nor, 4. In the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> at his Ordination. Nor, 5. In the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Treatiſes deſigned to inſtruct <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in all the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of their Faith. 6. From the Confeſſions of <hi>Romiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> with an Anſwer to the Arguments of Mr. <hi>Mumford</hi> for <hi>Traditions;</hi> and a <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> That the <hi>Heathens</hi> made the ſame Plea from <hi>Tradition</hi> as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> do; and that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Fathers to it doth fully juſtifie the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All theſe four Books Written by the Reverend</hi> D. Whitby, <hi>D.D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Exhortation to <hi>Charity,</hi> (and a Word of Comfort) to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants: Being a <hi>Sermon</hi> Preached at <hi>Steeple</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> upon occaſion of the Collection for Relief of the Poor Proteſtants in this Kingdom, lately fled from <hi>Ireland:</hi> By <hi>Samuel Bold,</hi> Rector of <hi>Steeple.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47184:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
